<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sober sadnes: or Historicall observations vpon the proceedings, pretences, &amp; designs of a prevailing party in both Houses of Parliament. With the resolution of all loyall subjects, and true Protestants of the Church of England thereupon.</title>
            <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96838</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E94_28</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8232</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873250</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873250</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155794</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96838)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155794)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 16:E94[28])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sober sadnes: or Historicall observations vpon the proceedings, pretences, &amp; designs of a prevailing party in both Houses of Parliament. With the resolution of all loyall subjects, and true Protestants of the Church of England thereupon.</title>
                  <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 47, [1] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Webb Book-seller, neer Queens Colledge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M .DC. XLIII. [1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>There is a good deal of detailed information in his book, which is clearly the work of a Royalist in close touch with affairs in London, cf. Madan.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Laurence Womock. cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 3".</note>
                  <note>Illustration facing t.p., having caption in banner: Estote proditores Betraye your Country.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:155794:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155794:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SOBER SADNES:</hi> OR <hi>Hiſtoricall Obſervations</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PON <hi>The Proceedings, Pretences, &amp; Deſigns of a prevailing party in both Houſes of</hi> PARLIAMENT. With the reſolution of all loyall Subjects, and true Proteſtants of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> thereupon.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH</hi> 33. 1.</bibl>
               <p>Woe to thee that ſpoileſt, and thou waſt not ſpoiled: and that dealeſt treacherouſly, and they dealt not treacherouſly with thee: when thou ceaſeſt to ſpoile, thou ſhalt be ſpoiled.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAIAH</hi> 29. 16.</bibl>
               <p>Surely your turning of things upſide downe ſhall be eſteemed as the Potters clay.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed for</hi> W. Webb <hi>Book-ſeller, neer</hi> Queens Colledge. M. DC. XLIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:155794:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155794:2"/>
            <head>A Preface to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He particular <hi>exorbitances</hi> of mans life are ſo many thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>off-ſets</hi> from that bitter root, his <hi>originall deprava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> He that allowes his ſoule to be impaired only in her inferiour faculties, his deniall of the reſt is proof enough againſt him. <hi>His mind and conſcience is defiled,</hi> and in this conſtitution makes <hi>ſnares</hi> of every <hi>clew</hi> ordain'd to guide him; as wel thoſe of divine, as thoſe of humane <hi>ſpinning.</hi> Being ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that his <hi>lampe</hi> by nature wants <hi>oyle</hi> and <hi>trimming,</hi> if hee pretends to have his defect of light ſupply'd by the extemporary <hi>flaſhes</hi> of inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he preſently inviteth <hi>Satan</hi> to be his guide with his dark Lantherne. When this light is ſet up before him, he thinks he hath leſt all the world b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſides in that <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> to which himſelfe travelleth, miſtaking <hi>ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> for the <hi>ſtraight way.</hi> This light (kindled on purpoſe to diſtract and dazle) puts him into a reſtleſſe <hi>phrenzie.</hi> This <hi>phrenzie</hi> is put upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>zeale,</hi> and every murther that <hi>zeale</hi> commits is a reputed <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi> The time will come, ſaith <hi>Christ, That he that killeth you will thinke he doth God ſervice.</hi> This <hi>ſtrange fire</hi> as <hi>wilde</hi> as 'tis, hath been offer'd up by ſundry <hi>Sects</hi> in all <hi>Ages</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> but through the wiſdome and juſtice of God, hath been diſpos'd to conſume the <hi>offerers.</hi> The <hi>Factious</hi> of our times are like to draw the ſame Judgement upon their own heads, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we may conjecture by the ſudden anſwer to that <hi>Petition</hi> ſo often repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Lord <hi>Brooke</hi> before his laſt enterpriſe: <hi>viz. Lord, if this action be not for thy glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, cut me off ſpeedily.</hi> No armour is of <hi>proofe</hi> to withſtand <hi>God,</hi> ſo earneſtly <hi>challenged</hi> to the vindication of his owne <hi>glory.</hi> This <hi>Lord</hi> being once demanded (according to the uſuall <hi>ſalutation</hi> of the times) what <hi>newes?</hi> reply'd, hee could tell no <hi>newes,</hi> but hee could tell <hi>miracles;</hi> and <hi>theſe</hi> were nothing elſe but that ſtrange <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> which God had given againſt all <hi>advantages</hi> on the other ſide to his <hi>Annointed.</hi> I'le leave the <hi>expreſſion</hi> betwixt <hi>jeſt</hi> and <hi>earneſt.</hi> Every man may carry it as his iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ement ſhall direct him: But ſurely <hi>wiſe men</hi> are of opinion his Lordſhip had at that time little reaſon to ſpeake <hi>Ironically.</hi> Whether he <hi>marcht</hi> againſt the light of a <hi>ſelf-conviction,</hi> I determine not. There are that take upon them to <hi>cite</hi> all men living to the <hi>Barre</hi> of their private <hi>conſure;</hi> and not confining their <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſdiction</hi> here, <hi>ſit</hi> upon the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death</hi> of thoſe <hi>ſoules</hi> that have paſt their <hi>accounts</hi> to their owne <hi>Maſters.</hi> Let them reioyce in this <hi>practice</hi> that retaine it, as a <hi>distinguiſhing</hi> marke of their <hi>profeſſion.</hi> For my part I ſhall ſay no more then I may ſay ſafely: God in his wiſdome thought it not fit to advance his owne <hi>glory</hi> any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>action</hi> of ſuch an <hi>Inſtrument;</hi> And let his <hi>example</hi> be an admonition unto <hi>us</hi> that have ſurviv'd <hi>him,</hi> to premeditate at leaſt our
<pb facs="tcp:155794:3"/> 
               <hi>imprecations,</hi> conſidering how ſoone <hi>omnipotencie</hi> can returne <hi>them</hi> into our owne <hi>boſomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If men would ſeriouſly conſider how many <hi>parties</hi> have followed the direction of ſuch <hi>guides</hi> as pretended to <hi>infallibility,</hi> and yet their <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> hath been <hi>Rebellion,</hi> their <hi>faith Faction,</hi> and their <hi>zeale</hi> a <hi>murthering</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> innocents by a common conſtruction; and then <hi>reflect</hi> upon the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>pers</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> times, and then have been dieted: This might prove <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n effectuall meanes to recover <hi>ſome,</hi> and prevent the farther ſpreading of this dangerous <hi>leprofie</hi> in others. To this purpoſe ſerves this inſuing diſcovery; wherein a ſtrict account is taken of <hi>three</hi> generall <hi>heads,</hi> as the moſt received <hi>ſummes,</hi> out of which our <hi>miſeries</hi> have been more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cularly <hi>disburſed.</hi> They are the <hi>proceedings, pretences,</hi> and <hi>deſignes</hi> of, &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>deſignes</hi> we ſee the <hi>end</hi> aimed at: In the <hi>pretences,</hi> the <hi>way</hi> by which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey have travail'd towards the <hi>end:</hi> And in their <hi>proceedings,</hi> their <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe</hi> in that <hi>way.</hi> We ſhall decline that exact <hi>method</hi> uſed in <hi>handling</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> becauſe what are <hi>praecognita</hi> to them (as all <hi>deſignes</hi> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the contrivers) are <hi>poſt cognita</hi> to us. We can deduce them but by way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>inference,</hi> and therefore having laid downe the other as the two <hi>promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> we ſhall draw theſe into the <hi>concluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In their <hi>proceedings:</hi> If our diſcourſe be guilty of too much <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>xity</hi> (as it may be to thoſe who have heard them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o oft repeated) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ember we are to relate by what <hi>meanes</hi> their <hi>party</hi> grew to be ſo <hi>potent;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſties</hi> ſundry invitations unto <hi>Peace,</hi> and readineſſe to embrace <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etitions</hi> of that nature; whiles they labour to <hi>ſtifle</hi> or <hi>reiect</hi> them; The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ndry <hi>practices</hi> they have uſed to ſupport their declining <hi>cauſe</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> and how violently they have borne themſelves up, as well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainſt ſundry <hi>diſcouragements,</hi> as againſt the ſolid grounds of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Amongſt their <hi>pretences</hi> wee ſhall find theſe <hi>colours:</hi> The <hi>Defence</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> by <hi>rooting</hi> out <hi>Epiſcopacy, Scandalous Ministers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luralities,</hi> and the <hi>Temporall employments</hi> of the <hi>Clergie;</hi> The <hi>ſecurity</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is <hi>Maiesties Royall Perſon, Crowne,</hi> and <hi>Dignity;</hi> with the <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Property</hi> of the <hi>Subiect;</hi> The <hi>triall</hi> of <hi>Delinquents,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their <hi>deſignes:</hi> The <hi>ſubverſion</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> both of <hi>Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> found upon good <hi>evidence;</hi> with a ſerious <hi>recollection</hi> of our <hi>ſelves</hi> to the <hi>practice</hi> of a reſolved <hi>loyaltie.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155794:3"/>
            <head>The COMPLAINT of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome againſt the evill Members of both Houſes, who have upon deſigne brought in <hi>Ruine</hi> under a pretence of <hi>Reformation.</hi> Relating to that former <hi>Complaint</hi> made by the Citie and Counties adjacent.</head>
            <p>WE are glad our brethren are ſo well recovered out of their <hi>Lethargie,</hi> as to be able to informe us, that they are growne ſenſible of their miſeries. Wee confeſſe, our ſelves lay ſtupified in a too unhappy dreame or tameneſſe, till this Alarm did awaken us; and now beſides the ſympathie and compaſſion that we have of the afflictions of our neighbours, the ſenſe of our owne ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings is ſo ſharpe, that wee are forced to <hi>circumflect</hi> the ſad accents of their juſt <hi>Complaint.</hi> More neede not be added to that <hi>Relation</hi> by way of ſupplement, to perfect the horrible <hi>Anatomy</hi> of our miſeries: Yet we conceive it will not be in vaine to diſcover who they were that (pretending to <hi>reforme</hi> even our happineſſe, and then to ſecure that happineſſe by ſuch impregnable fortifications, as God never yet vouchſafed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in temporall bleſſings withall) did at the ſame time no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but make that interruption and breach of our ſweet reſt, which betrayed us unto all theſe diſtempers which have ſucceeded; and how our repoſe, which ſhould be prevalent to reſtore us, is now diſcontinued, as it was at firſt diſturbed, by the very ſame men againſt our wills.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:155794:4"/>
            <p> Under the pretence of the worke of God theſe diſtractions crept in upon us and what ever the deſigne be (we ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine that anon) Gods title is made ſo ſtrong to it, aſwell by States men as Divines, that they thinke his omnipotency as deeply ingaged, as their owne deare intereſts, or ſeduced con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences to goe through with it. But we muſt profeſſe, that what that <hi>great worke of God is,</hi> which their actions aime at, hath never beene ſufficiently, can never be unanimouſly (by themſelves) declared. God hath many workes, and ſome that are fit to goe thorow none, but thoſe accurſed hands of <hi>Judas;</hi> and if they would prevaile with us for our <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> they muſt produce ſome prophecie; that infallibly makes them the ruine of their <hi>King and Countrey.</hi> But yet we ſhould take leave to tell them, that it is not ſuch a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table employment to be made the rod of Gods anger, becauſe though his wiſedome uſeth, his goodneſſe loveth not the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of his childrens correction: The rod is alwayes burnt for doing malicious execution.</p>
            <p>Was the worke to chaſtiſe the pride of the King (as ſome have intimated) with a greater; or as ſome thought and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt freely, to root out <hi>Epiſcopacy, Deanes,</hi> and <hi>Chapters,</hi> that they might eſtabliſh their owne preaching Miniſtry, or them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Revenues? This would have beene a glorious <hi>Reformation</hi> of thoſe grand errours of their fore-fathers chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, when that true Devotion that had expatiated their hearts, opened their treaſures to, and made them too laviſh in their expences upon Gods worſhip. Now the effects of that zeale which burneth in our <hi>Worthies,</hi> are to bring downe the price of our <hi>Religion,</hi> to ſerve God at a cheaper rate, and to offer Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of that which coſt them nothing. What ever the <hi>worke</hi> was we ſee what worke it hath made amongſt us; and if we obſerve the ſtepes by which it hath aſcended, we ſhall eaſily perceive<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Authors thought it could not ſucceed otherwiſe then by violence. What ever the modell be, the ſtructure was not likely to be ſet up as the holy Temple was, without any ſound of <hi>Axe</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er</hi> but <hi>with confuſed noiſe, and garments rolled in bloud.</hi> The truth is, deſparing of <hi>Gods ſpeed,</hi> we have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155794:4"/> cauſe to beleeve they reſolved to take the Devils. Hence were thoſe Tumults raiſed, Riots juſtified, ſome whereof were of that diſperate nature, that the <hi>Ring-leaders</hi> of them made it the <hi>emphaſis</hi> of their enraged paſſion, to cry out, <hi>The King is the Traytor: The King is not fit to live: The Prince would go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne better.</hi> Thoſe that heard theſe things, and are ready to make proofe of them, have good reaſon to thinke His Majeſtie was driven from <hi>London,</hi> and not much miſled by thoſe evill Counſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lours that advertiſed him of the danger.</p>
            <p>Thus was the King and many of His Subjects little better entertained in the ſtreets: And did His Majeſties friends finde any better wellcome in both Houſes? were not thoſe Houſes made a Sanctuary to the moſt deſperate <hi>Delinquents,</hi> if they had learned to tune their Votes to the prevailing, becauſe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent partly; whileſt gallant ſober gentlemen, who preferred ſolid reaſon and their owne conſcience, before any popular Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, were poſted up and baniſh't from them? For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the former. I need adde no more to the Inſtances in the <hi>Complaint,</hi> then Maſter <hi>Griffith,</hi> who being guilty of a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous attempt upon the Lady <hi>Sidlyes</hi> chaſtity, and complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of for the ſame, yet the Houſe was ſo farre from ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it ſelfe to be purged of this <hi>able</hi> Member<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they were pleaſed to advance him to an honourable office (if any office may be ſtiled honourable) in their <hi>Holy Army:</hi> And this is the man that was lately ſent out in ſo much pompe with his ſilver Trumpets.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, becauſe ſome worthy Members of both Houſes were privy to more of their deſignes, then they could with a cleare heart aſſent unto; 'tis probable (though for no other reaſon) if this violent party could have conſtrued their actions (by any rules or exceptions) into Treaſon, they ſhould have loſt their heads to ſecure their memories from betraying Cloſe-Committee ſecrets. Thus many Gentlemen of knowne integrity were deprived of thoſe priviledges wherewith they were inveſted aſwell by the <hi>Authority</hi> of the King, as the <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage</hi> of their Countrey; and expoſed to the rage of a rude multitude, cauſeleſly incenſed: and yet if they fled after their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:155794:5"/> Soveraigne, to ſeeke that ſecurity at a diſtance, which (retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a good conſcience) they could not promiſe themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>influence</hi> of both Houſes, they were preſently declared <hi>Delinquents,</hi> as if they could not be friends to themſelves, nor loyall to their King, without perill to the Kingdome: and after the power of the Countrey refuſed to bring them up, (finding no juſt ground for it) an <hi>Army</hi> is voted to be levied to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem; and then all their miſcarriages (poſſibly but of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ailty) being ſumm'd up together, if the totall would have amounted (a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> eaſily might have done) to a <hi>conſtructive</hi> Treaſon, their lifes had beene rendred a prey to a <hi>Legiſlative,</hi> that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>an unlimited power, as blind as a man's ſelfe-will or malice, and their fortunes an oblation to theſe mens ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us having caſt out the great ones, who were not like to fall into<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or continue in their owne hands and cunningly ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled with the reſt; they ſoone packt their Cardes ſo, as the die ſhould never be carried (in any matter of conſequence, for in triviall things they could differ upon deſigne) againſt them. The violent courſe they tooke made a ſtrong ſide quickly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and indeed the ſtreame grew too violent to be interrupted; and whatſoever was done by the wiſedome of His Majeſtie to turne the <hi>Torrent,</hi> that it might not bring this <hi>Inundation,</hi> which it hath now brought upon His Royall Government; ſuch was the power and reputation that theſe men had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed amongſt the people, not by their owne merit, but His Majeſties <hi>Acts of grace</hi> conveighed through their hands to them, that it was eaſily made uſe of to His Majeſties diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty upon a timely diſcovery of the firſt riſing of this proud malignant tumour, applied nothing but the gentle <hi>lenitives</hi> of his favour to aſſwage and allay it: At laſt after the emptying of a whole treaſury of acts of grace unto his people, finding them ineffectuall to ſtop the current of their blind fury, and deſirous to prevent thoſe inconveniences, which we now by that meanes groane under (juſtice being denyed to his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters on this behalfe) was drawne into a neceſſity of going
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155794:5"/> into the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> in his owne perſon, ro demand the principall Engineers (as His Majeſty had then good reaſon to conceive, and all men now to ſuſpect) of this deſtructive ſtratagem. And ſeeing what we now ſee, and feeling what we now feele, we might have had a juſt occaſion to have given that miſtake the Title of an happy <hi>errour,</hi> as being a likely meanes, if it had taken effect, to have prevented theſe diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers that have inſued, and ſettled our peace and truth to the generall contentment of the whole Kingdome, and all this without any prejudice to thoſe mens reputation, if that charge had not beene proved againſt them. But this errour was a weapon they have made much uſe of in all their Remonſtrances and Declarations, and indeed the onely one that hath beene with any colour alleadged to their advantage. As for the bringing up of the <hi>Engliſh Army,</hi> that was but a leaden Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that never wounded the Kings honour amongſt them that underſtood it truly. But this errour in His Majeſty was reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a crime of a greater magnitude, then the Treaſon it ſelfe whereof the Members were accuſed, and His Majeſty is <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dighted</hi> for it in every <hi>pamphlet</hi> before the <hi>barre</hi> of every vulgar Judgement, where uſually the charge is not ſooner read, then the ſentence of condemnation pronounced.</p>
            <p>After they had raiſed their greatneſſe to this height upon thoſe prejudices, which they had laid againſt His Majeſty (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciall upon this miſtake for which he hath d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne <hi>pennance</hi> ſo often in their foule ſheets) they reſolved either to ſettle what their fond ambition had deſigned, or elſe to ſacrifice the peace and happine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe of the Kingdome to their owne fury. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving failed (God be praiſed) of ſucceſſe hitherto, they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue as far diſtant in heart from any inclinations to our redreſſe, as the meanes is which they have propounded to effect it.</p>
            <p>When they ſeized upon the Kings <hi>Militia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> they made faſt addreſſes to our Ruine. And ſince we know by a ſad, a very ſad experience what a long and effectuall progreſſe they have made in it. It cannot but ſeeme ſtrange that they ſhould preſume with ſo much confidence to derive a power of taking <hi>Armes</hi> to themſelves, and ground it upon the <hi>fundamentall lawes</hi> of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155794:6"/> Kingdome, and yet (haveing ſet up as ſtrict an <hi>inquiſition</hi> for <hi>preſidents</hi> as for <hi>Del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nquents)</hi> now after ſo many monethes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucubrations, not one fragment of Law produced to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Nay, if our owne skill and the opinion of learned and honeſt Judges, (who muſt not be conſulted with in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie) deceive us not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it is an attempt which the Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides againſt under no lower Title then <hi>high treaſon.</hi> And yet a circulation of reports had ſo charmed us, and breathed ſo many cold feares and jealouſies upon us, and theſe ſo preſt by the weight of that Authority, which (whiles it moved upon its own Center) we highly reverenced, that growing deafe to our owne duty at home, we uſerpt the office of our Soveraigne, for our protection againſt pretended forraigne dangers. But after a little ſucceſſion of time had undeceived us, we perceived no other dangers threatning us, then ſuch as were now a caſting in that very <hi>mould,</hi> which (we were told) was made for our ſecurity.</p>
            <p>The hedge of our <hi>Government</hi> (becauſe ſome <hi>Weeds</hi> acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally ſprung up in it, or elſe for that it had many <hi>thornes,</hi> as all good <hi>fences</hi> ſhould have, to afflict tranſgreſſors that run o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it) was cried quite downe, and pul'd as low as <hi>libertiniſme</hi> could lay it, ſo that our faire and fruitfull <hi>incloſure</hi> was laid into a wild and waſte <hi>Common.</hi> Indeed they had very provedently deſigned a new <hi>paile,</hi> but the chife workemen could not agree in what faſhion to ſaw it out.</p>
            <p>And in the interim moſt men (as they were engaged or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged) had quitted thoſe <hi>Trenches,</hi> which Almighty God had <hi>digg'd</hi> for them in his holy <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and waited to take Sanctuary in the <hi>Fortifications</hi> of their projecting. Now to raiſe theſe (becauſe they ware to encounter with many diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuties) they muſt have the <hi>Sword</hi> as well as the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rewell,</hi> that (if need were) they might <hi>build</hi> and <hi>fight</hi> together. To this end (the <hi>Scots</hi> who had beene kept long upon this deſigne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſmiſt) they attempted to wreſt the ſword out of the hand of the King, the proper owner. A fatall attempt that <hi>preſaged</hi> perill to the <hi>aſſailants;</hi> for <hi>he that</hi> (thus) <hi>takes the ſword</hi> (againſt that authority that hath the ſole power of it) <hi>ſhall periſh</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:155794:6"/> 
               <hi>by the ſword.</hi> And truly God hath miraculouſly made it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that his <hi>Vicegerent beareth not the ſword in vaine.</hi> Not that His Majeſty delights to unſheath the ſword of Juſtice, more then for exemplary puniſhment, though he hath lately met with ſuch extreme provocations, as were enough to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate the ſofteſt nature into fury. We find a ſweet ſtraine of grace and mercy run through the whole <hi>Tragedy</hi> of his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and doubtleſſe had there been a ſuitable correſpondence in the inclinations of others, the Kingdome had not at this day been ſtained in ſo deep a <hi>die</hi> of blood. How much of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted <hi>rights</hi> did His Majeſty freely ſacrifice for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of his people? If we ſhould reckon up all his acts of grace (as well thoſe which have beene abuſed to our diſadvantage, as thoſe whereof we are in hope to reape the fruit hereafter) they will abundantly recompence all thoſe preſſures which evill <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours</hi> had formerly brought upon us. And (as if he could deny his people nothing whilſt they ſuffered him to keepe any thing for himſelfe) he graciouſly offered to commit to <hi>hands of their owne chooſing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſo large a ſhare of the <hi>Militia,</hi> as might have rendred them ſecure, if ſecurity (in a juſt and legall way) had beene all they ſought for. But ſome of them having got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten too great an intereſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as well in the <hi>faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> as in the <hi>affections</hi> of the people, (who could not prevaile with themſelves to be perſwaded, they aimed leſſe at His Majeſties Honour, then at the publike good) in confidence of their ſtrength came roundly to the buſineſſe, and ſeized upon that by force, which (their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry petitions can witneſſe, for theſe were not petitions of <hi>right)</hi> was not due unto them. And now the King hath as much reaſon to exhibite a petition of <hi>right</hi> for the ſecuring of his <hi>property,</hi> as ever the Subject had. His Forts and Townes are kept by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, his goods arreſted, and his owne Armes taken up to reſiſt him to his face, and theſe will not be reſtorid, till he conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to a <hi>compoſition.</hi> Nineteen propoſitions are ſent downe to him, that His Majeſty would be content with a <hi>twentieth</hi> part, whileſt the reſt of the <hi>Crowne</hi> is ſhared betweene both Houſes. Theſe ſeemed to be very ſtrange propoſitions, in the opinion of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyall</hi> Subjects, who wiſht their King as much glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:155794:7"/> as theſe men had promiſed him. Yet theſe were ſo far from altering His Majeſties deſires of peace, that he vouchſafed to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer them; and to give either the thing demanded, or a reaſon of his deniall which was better; and yet ſo farre from ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that wiſe men did equally admire the Kings <hi>grace,</hi> and their <hi>unthankefulneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhould His Majeſty doe? It was high time (after ſo many threatning votes, and hoſtility actually exerciſed at <hi>Hull</hi> againſt His Royall Perſon) to provide for the defence of Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and His good Subjects that attended Him, leſt their <hi>loyalty</hi> ſhould betray them to inevitable deſtruction. Hence a <hi>guard</hi> was raiſed for the ſafety of His Majeſties Royall Perſon, and that conſiſted of the chiefe <hi>Gentry,</hi> that could not reaſonably be preſumed to contribute aſsiſtance to the <hi>enſlaving</hi> of themſelves &amp; their poſterity. And yet this ſmall <hi>guard</hi> is preſently declared to be raiſed for the ſubverſion of <hi>Parliament</hi> &amp; in that of all our native <hi>liberties.</hi> His Majeſty was not ſo happy in His meanes of <hi>undeceiving</hi> His good people, (as He hath been ſince) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of His <hi>Royall Word</hi> being blaſted (to gaine credit to themſelves) by their black-mouth'd <hi>Remonſtrances.</hi> And yet all theſe reports (though their credit was much improved by the <hi>Authority</hi> of both Houſes) had a very ample and ſufficient <hi>confutation</hi> by ſeverall meſſages of peace ſent from <hi>Nottingham.</hi> Now if we looke to the reception, it was nothing ſuitable to the errand; which (if we may conclude from the entertainment) was ſo farre from finding a complyance of inclinations, that it met with very little <hi>Civility</hi> or good nature amongſt them. For interpreting all theſe Acts of <hi>grace</hi> but inſtances of his <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> they were more deſperately bent, and urged by new votes, that their Army might advance to make a ſpeedy aſſault upon them. Where by the way let me hint thus much: If thoſe ſeverall meſſages proceed out of <hi>weakeneſſe,</hi> we may take notice of a ſpeciall Providence, that ſo ſuddenly encreaſ'd His Majeſties Forces even to <hi>admiration.</hi> But if the ſaid propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals were the genuine offspring of a gracious Prince then they were extremely unthankfull to ſlight the noble meſſengers, and ſo ſcornfully to caſt ſo many offers of a peace behind them. As
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155794:7"/> weake as His Majeſty was, Almighty God preſerved him from their fury, and was his ſafe <hi>convoy</hi> to <hi>Edge-hill;</hi> where (having been formerly advertiſed of a petition) he might very well have expected ſome handſome addreſſe before an alarum from them. 'Tis true, they ſay a very humble Petition (ſubſcribed with a deale of Ceremony by both Houſes) was committed to the hands of the <hi>Generall (the Earle of Eſſex,)</hi> but it ſeems it was ordered (if they conceived it for their advantage, which they ſuppoſed they had then gotten) to be delivered and made report of by the mouth of a <hi>Cannon.</hi> Well, theſe men, who were too mighty to imbrace an offered peace (as Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence would have it) were ſo diſcomfited (if we may have leave to ſpeak the truth) that by that time His Majeſty was advanced to <hi>Colebrooks,</hi> their weakneſſe had inclined them (and in good time be it ſpoken, it was the firſt ſtep they ſet) to an <hi>Accommodation.</hi> And His Majeſty (not triumphing in the ruine of His worſt ſubjects, being a loſing <hi>Conquerour</hi> in ſo ſad a victory, nor deſirous to improve the uſe of His ſword, beyond the recovering of His juſt rights; and ſettling that law by which He holds them) met them with a gracious and ready cheerfulneſſe to accompliſh it. But in the interim, whileſt the Meſſengers are making their addreſſes to His Majeſty, the ſouldiers purſuing their ſad though juſt and neceſſary imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, advanced to <hi>Brainceford,</hi> and becauſe they put the <hi>Red</hi> Regiment and ſome others (as is conceived) to the worſt, they are accuſed of <hi>treachery.</hi> Nay the King Himſelfe muſt be ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, though (if the matter be well examined) they had no reaſon to complaine, but that the day went againſt them: For can a ſouldier expect <hi>quarter</hi> before he askes it? Or an Army imagine to be at <hi>truce</hi> in the view of the enemy before a <hi>truce</hi> be moved? In other places upon <hi>Treaties</hi> of this nature, Courts of Guard are doubled; and were they ſo unacquainted with the cuſtomes of warre, as not to provide againſt all advantages of the enemy? I know not what they expected from His Majeſty, but I am ſure His Majeſty never found more faire play from <hi>them,</hi> (though His ſubjects) nor ſo much as he might have done from a <hi>forraigne</hi> Enemy. Admit they did upon ſecond
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:155794:8"/> thoughts ſend a Meſſenger to deſire a <hi>Ceſſation</hi> from all hoſtile acts; we know the buſineſſe was put in execution before the Meſſengers arrivall, nay, it ſtopt him in the midſt of his journey. If they had beene deſirous to prevent all further <hi>effuſion</hi> of bloud, the motion ſhould have been made more ſeaſonably (as it might have been by their firſt Meſſengers) to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. What <hi>Revelations</hi> other men may goe upon, we know not; but we are ſure His Majeſty doth not pretend to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with their deſires by inſpiration. And His Majeſties forces had great reaſon to uſe all meanes to fruſtrate the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage which their enemies had taken. Wee know how their Souldiers had almoſt on all ſides invironed him, and new forces raiſed in <hi>London,</hi> advanced with ſpeed towards them, and why might not his Majeſty advance forward, as well as His Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries? If they ſay, their Generall did but purſue their order, which was given the night before their Meſſengers ſet forth, they doe but tell us in effect, that they had laid the deſigne ſo cunningly, that themſelves might take any advantage freely; but if the King did the like, it was predeſtinated to be called Treachery.</p>
            <p>We could tell of gracious Letters directed to the Houſe at that time, but intercepted by their Army, and committed cloſe priſoners to the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> pockets, for no other crime then bringing peaceable intimations. The truth is, the mannagery of this Warre was committed to ſuch hands as were glad of any occaſion, colourably to decline the way of peace: For what did they ſay; <hi>His Majeſty is yet too ſtrong to bee dealt withall by a Treaty;</hi> which implieth, they muſt endeavour to ſecure His Royall Perſon by the ruine of thoſe whoſe loyalty hath raiſed them up to guard it, that they may the better ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert his Government before their owne deſigne could bee ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</p>
            <p>Whilſt all their preparations are for battaile, His Majeſty labours ſtill for peace; to which He once againe invites them by a Meſſage ſent from <hi>Reading:</hi> But they are now growne deafe on both eares to Propoſitions of that nature; and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name of Accommodation (for we know the man that ſaid
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155794:8"/> he hated it) is become odious and malignant. They breath forth nothing but challenge and defiance againſt His Majeſty; and theſe men that could cheerfully entertaine ſuitors of any condition, or any mans procuring: whilſt their Courtſhip was taught to wooe them not to embrace what was fit or profitable for the Kingdome, but what their own affections had made choice of, in order to the ſatisfying of their ambition. Now they grow coy, and frowne upon all ſuch as ſollicite them in the name of peace; as if ſhe were ſo farre from being an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient in it, that ſhe were the onely obſtacle to our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the bleeding miſeries of the Kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> (which muſt wholly be laid upon the ſcore, who have obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted their reliefe through theſe diſtempers of their owne rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) ſpurr'd them on to frame their ſad Complaints into Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, to which his Majeſty lent a gracious eare, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to contribute aſſiſtance in any way that could be propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Him: but the two Houſes (who were formerly very angry, that they might not have all the honour of reducing that wretched Kingdome) afforded little pity, leſſe aid unto them; many bitter diſcontented ſpirits raiſing ſcruples and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings at the Petition, inſtead of applying themſelves to the reliefe of their diſtreſſes for the preſent, or to make a peace with His Majeſty, (as was deſired) whereby they might bee enabled to aſſiſt them for the future.</p>
            <p>Then the many prodigious tokens of our ruine here at home began to awaken us, and make us ſollicitous for our owne ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The moſt ſubſtantiall Citizens meeting together in no other ominous or formidable poſture, then with gloves on their hands to move a Petition for peace; and they are accuſed for committing a riot, and impriſoned, whilſt forces ſent to aſſault and murder them, are interpreted (by their great Doctors of the Law) to keep the peace of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Theſe men that have ſo long beguiled the people with falſe Alarmes, and never more then by pretending to have bent all their endeavours to work a good underſtanding and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation with His Majeſty, have been ſo farre from giving
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155794:9"/> countenance to Petitions of that nature, that all their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours have been (and ſometimes by Meſſengers directed on purpoſe) to ſtrangle them; and ſuch <hi>Gentlemen</hi> as have been imployed in their Countrey on ſuch <hi>errands,</hi> have for that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-ſake been plundered, their Horſes taken from them, (as our neighbours of <hi>Eſſex</hi> are able to depoſe;) and the authority of the Houſes by which they were taken, either cannot or will not be effectually exerciſed to recover them, but an <hi>appeale</hi> muſt be made from them unto the <hi>cloſe-Committee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what! is there no excuſe to be alleadged to take off the blemiſh of this action? Truly, their web is not of ſo plain a ſpinning, but they have many pretty coloured threds runne thorow it. They'le tell us, <hi>'Tis no more needfull for the people to ſpurre them on to their duty, then lawfull to direct them in it; ſuch Petitions are ſawcy breaches of their Priviledges: They have the ſole power to judge of ſenſe and reaſon, and the dangers of the Kingdome.</hi> Indeed they have moſt reaſon to be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the nature of thoſe <hi>dangers,</hi> that were firſt <hi>premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and ſince of their owne actuall forging. Certainly, as theſe men have laboured to thruſt out both our eyes, that we might not ſee; ſo they would extinguiſh our memories, that we might remember nothing. They ſhould engage ſome of their inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to teach us an Art of forgetfulneſſe, in behalfe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Acts</hi> in the time of their owne <hi>reigne,</hi> as well as an Art of memory, in behalfe of ſome ſufferings under the reigne of our Soveraignes at leaſt, they ſhall have voted an <hi>oblivion,</hi> that their <hi>owne</hi> late <hi>practices</hi> of encouraging <hi>Petitioners</hi> of another ſtraine, as <hi>bold</hi> and <hi>directory,</hi> might not riſe up to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould it be reputed a breach of good manners for Petitioners to ſuggeſt the meanes of their owne redreſſe? Every man knowes beſt where his owne ſhooe pinches. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity ſtands not upon Ceremonies, and doubtleſs Beggars may be chooſers, when the choice is, Whetherthey will ſubmit to their owne ruine againſt Law and Equity, or maintaine thoſe Rights wherewith they are legally inveſted, under the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a gracious Soveraigne, againſt the ſpoile and rapine of an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> power.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:155794:9"/>
            <p> Well! if men that have lived under the dominion of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Sol,</hi> (being taught by their effects to put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them) finding the firſt to be incomparably moſt malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant begin to deſire to be look't upon with a more propitious influence. If it be imputed for a crime to theſe men to Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the ſtorm (without doubt raiſed by ſpirits, in whom the Prince of the ayre worketh, who worketh in all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedience) might be calmed, that they might enjoy their old comfortable Sun-ſhine: Yet me-thinks a motion for Peace (which no State till our dayes condemned for an <hi>ill Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter)</hi> made by one of their owne Members, might have paſt without exception. That grand Aſſertor of the publike <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> who in <hi>civility</hi> gave the King the <hi>title</hi> of a <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> when he kept the <hi>Authority</hi> to himſelfe, and confounded the undoubted <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>Crowne,</hi> with the never-heard-of <hi>Priviledges</hi> of Parliament, we meane Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham,</hi> (who out of a remorſe of conſcience, that he had been the prime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of this combuſtion, or out of an apprehenſion of an unlikelihood of prevailing, curſed himſelfe) moved no leſſe then <hi>three</hi> main <hi>wheeles</hi> at once, to ſet forward the work of an <hi>Accommodation.</hi> (Thoſe Letters of his to the Earles of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> and to the <hi>Speaker</hi> of the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> had been as well worth the peoples reading (if they had had a purpoſe to let the people ſee any thing tending to their peace and happineſſe) as thoſe from the Earle of <hi>Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> of the totall <hi>defeat</hi> which he had given Sir <hi>Ralph Hopton;</hi> (of the truth of which the Houſes have ſince been ſufficiently informed:) Or thoſe other of the Lord <hi>Fairefax,</hi> interlined with an ordinary <hi>gloſſe,</hi> and ſo printed for the <hi>benefit</hi> of the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters forth. But theſe from Sir <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> did not ſpeak to the ſenſe of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> that uſe to ſit in <hi>Merchant Taylors Hall</hi> at midnight, and therefore were not fit to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated. And if we enquire how they were accepted, we ſhall find that they had but little better <hi>welcome</hi> then the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of peace had to both Houſes. Such a <hi>jealouſie</hi> is preſently raiſed againſt him, that though he had committed <hi>Treaſon</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his King, to become their <hi>faithfull ſervant,</hi> he begins to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155794:10"/> feare he ſhall be ſuffered to play <hi>Rex</hi> no longer, and complains of it: and many think if they had not more feared their owne then his <hi>periſhing</hi> by <hi>water,</hi> they had caſt him out of his <hi>Arke,</hi> for bringing this Olive branch to them.</p>
            <p>As they were averſe to motions of peace themſelves, ſo were they ſtrangely oppoſite to the tendring of ſuch ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to His Majeſty. Indeed they had reaſon; for (wanting competent evidence to ſpeak for them) they had often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended their own endeavours for peace, and made us believe that their frequent ſuits found His Majeſties eare inexorable. They were loth this device (which they had improv'd to ſome advantage amongſt the ordinary and leſſe knowing ſort of people, where moſt of their <hi>game</hi> lies) ſhould be diſcovered by any Petitioners perſonall attendance upon His Majeſty. Hence the Meſſengers that carried the Petition of <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, &amp;c.</hi> (though they had obtained a warrant from the Houſe for their free and ſafe paſſage) were ſurpriſed in the way; and upon ſearch made, ſome <hi>ſcandalous</hi> Pamphlets (as they called them for ſpeaking the truth) which in all probability had been committed to the Coachman, by that <hi>ſetting-Dogge</hi> that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered them; for the buſineſſe was a deep myſtery, and a very riddle to the Gentlemen: theſe were quickly found, (the ſearchers being pre-inſtructed in the plot) and ſo the Meſſengers were brought back againe, that they might not preſent their prayers to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>But His Majeſties Grace, as it invited all, ſo it found ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants from other parts of the Kingdome, whoſe diſtance from them was their beſt, if not their onely priviledge from inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and impriſonment: (We ſay nothing of the uſage of the <hi>Hartfordſhire</hi> Petitioners.) And after theſe men perceived that no <hi>art</hi> or <hi>induſtry</hi> could prevent it, but the Court would be frequented with ſollicitations of this nature, as long as it had a gracious <hi>eare,</hi> that took ſo much pleaſure to entertaine them; they directed a contrivall of a plauſible <hi>Petition</hi> to be carried to the King in the name of the <hi>Common-Councell.</hi> His Majeſty (never wanting to any thing that might repaire our unhappy breaches) vouchſafed a <hi>gratious</hi> anſwer; and ſuch as (if it had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:155794:10"/> been duely followed) had led us the way to very juſt, and no leſſe eaſie termes of Accommodation. But obſerve how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full theſe men are to worke a good underſtanding between the King and His Subjects: They breake through all the <hi>Liberties and Priviledges</hi> of the City (when we ſee the <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>Crowne trampled on,</hi> we cannot expect that any <hi>Priviledge</hi> ſhould ſtand before that of committing <hi>Treaſon.)</hi> And the people muſt not reade the Kings pleaſure, unleſſe they will put on <hi>Spectacles</hi> of Maſter <hi>Pyms</hi> making; nor heare His Majeſty ſpeake to them, unleſſe His authentick <hi>Text</hi> be firſt corrupted by falſe Comments.</p>
            <p>Was any <hi>County</hi> willing to be diſ-ingaged, deſirous (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they could not avoid it) to be ſad <hi>Spectators,</hi> rather then wild <hi>Actors</hi> in this bloudy <hi>Tragedy.</hi> Why ſuch a <hi>neutrality</hi> is voted to be <hi>malignant,</hi> ſuch a peace <hi>deſtructive?</hi> Though <hi>Articles</hi> be concluded, and ratified by their ſubſcriptions, the mutuall pledges of their faith, yet this muſt not <hi>atone</hi> thoſe neighbours, that knew not why, nor wherein they differed. Theſe men can finde Principles in the Schooles of <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> (and ſuch as are no where elſe to be found) that <hi>Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks, with Malignants, and men Popiſhly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected;</hi> (they runne parallel with them a great deale further) and hereupon they uſe thoſe new <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Keyes of their owne making, to reverſe all the <hi>bolts</hi> of theſe engagements, as if they had the ſame power to diſpenſe with conſciences, which they pretend to have in diſpenſe with Lawes of the Kingdome. Thus thoſe <hi>two</hi> Counties of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> when they had ſet <hi>their</hi> hands to the happy <hi>bonds</hi> of peace, and might have <hi>ſate quietly under their owne vines,</hi> were by <hi>Votes,</hi> (and nothing elſe) provoked (like creatures without reaſon) to worry one another. Theſe men that have <hi>ſo much</hi> of the <hi>publike faith,</hi> how <hi>little</hi> would they have of <hi>publike charity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have many Gentlemen put themſelves into a poſture of Warre, and obtained their Commiſſion onely to <hi>ſtalke</hi> by them, that they might the better furniſh themſelves for His Majeſties ſervice, which they aimed at? Have others, not a few, (and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155794:11"/> ſome of their neareſt and deareſt creatures) out of a late ſenſe of the weakneſſe of their <hi>cauſe,</hi> or <hi>party,</hi> or <hi>both,</hi> plaid the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers indeed, and turned <hi>faces about,</hi> with a reſolution and zeale to recompence His Majeſty by their good ſervice, for the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition which they had too long, but ignorantly made againſt him? Have others (who by the loſſe of a good <hi>fore-game,</hi> are taught to play an <hi>after-one)</hi> delivered up thoſe <hi>Commiſſions,</hi> that <hi>inabled</hi> them to fight againſt their owne <hi>honour,</hi> and ſpill all their <hi>noble</hi> bloud? Theſe, though they may prove dang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rous <hi>fore-runners</hi> of a grand <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> from the <hi>good worke,</hi> yet we muſt be pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſwaded th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y doe mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>animate</hi> unto the cauſe, then diſcourage them. The <hi>worke</hi> is look't upon, as if God himſelfe had actually <hi>cut</hi> it out, and appointed a <hi>ſelect</hi> company, (though never ſo few, if deſperately enough <hi>ſeditious)</hi> by an eſpeciall and immediate deſignation to finiſh it.</p>
            <p>Hence thoſe Propoſitions for <hi>Accommodation,</hi> which moſt part of the Kingdome had ſued for; and themſelves (finding a neceſſity in it, to take off that diſlike that began generally to fall upon them) had promiſed ſhould be prepa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, were delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ten or twelve weekes together; and before they are carried, are taught to ſpeake ſuch a language as doth but begge their juſt deniall. To anſwer theſe, His Majeſty is allowed but ten <hi>dayes,</hi> and (willing to cut the ſufferings of His people as ſhort as He could) He graciouſly diſpatched an anſwer almoſt in as few houres. He offers Propoſitions that a modeſt <hi>Conquerour</hi> would have accounted reaſonable, and yet ſubmits them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their <hi>owne,</hi> and a <hi>ceſſation</hi> to a <hi>Treaty.</hi> Theſe are brought to the Lords Houſe, and the violent <hi>party</hi> there not able to <hi>hinder</hi> it by <hi>Votes,</hi> endeavour to <hi>intangle</hi> it by <hi>intricacies.</hi> The <hi>hint</hi> is given to the <hi>leading</hi> men of the Houſe of Commons; and inſtead of voting a <hi>Ceſſation</hi> in order to the <hi>Treaty,</hi> they require an abſolute <hi>disbanding</hi> of all Forces, and yet no termes of peace concluded on: ſo that the reſult of all would be but this, the King muſt quit His <hi>Martiall</hi> attendants, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne Himſelfe up once againe into the hands of ſeditious Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults; (for thoſe muſt not be ſpoken againſt) &amp; then they ſhall be prepared for their Treaty. Some were ſo taken with this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155794:11"/> piece of Sophiſtry, that they openly boaſted; <hi>They had plaid their game too cunningly for His Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſty:</hi> Truly a maſter-piece of his <hi>Policie,</hi> whoſe deſignes (if they be not made fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate by a higher power) can finde no period but in utter <hi>ruine.</hi> Some 14 dayes were ſpent upon this <hi>plot,</hi> and yet it was not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ipened for His Majeſtie, which occaſioned another gracious Meſſage to prevent all miſtakes, (for His Majeſty muſt be very punctuall, or elſe He is ſure to be Declared <hi>Traytor)</hi> touching the limits of the Ceſſation; (which, as His Majeſtie was informed, they had at laſt voted.) What fruit all this <hi>ſeede</hi> will bring forth, perhaps the <hi>Spring</hi> may ſhew us; in the meane-while we are in a longing expectation, and muſt needs wonder, that having confined their King to ſo ſhort a time, (which His Majeſtie in compaſſion of the miſeries of His peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple made nine parts ſhorter too) themſelves ſhould not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſpin out their debates, when it lies in them onely (if they were not wanting to their duty, both to King and people) to put a preſent end to our calamities. At laſt (whiles we are penning theſe Obſervations) newes is brought of their <hi>conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcention</hi> to a <hi>Treaty,</hi> and (to ſhew what <hi>reall</hi> affections they have to peace or what a plentifull number they have all this while had againſt it) one of the two appointed by the Lords muſt needs be the Lord <hi>Say,</hi> whoſe <hi>long-practiſed</hi> principles of <hi>Schiſme</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve led him ſo far in the advancement of <hi>Sedition,</hi> that he is deſervedly proſcribed a Traytor by His Majeſty, ſo that (not able to doe more to obſtruct the way to our peace and happineſſe) they have brought the buſineſſe to this <hi>Dilemma;</hi> His Majeſty muſt either <hi>treat</hi> (and that face to face too) with a grand <hi>Rebell,</hi> (in all probability imployed on purpoſe to give a defeat to the whole <hi>Treaty)</hi> or elſe muſt expect to have the <hi>Odium</hi> of refuſing peace caſt upon Him.</p>
            <p>Well! to draw a concluſion from theſe, but too true and too ſad premiſes: If neither the gracious <hi>Meſſages</hi> and <hi>Invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of His Majeſty; nor the ſorrowfull prayers and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the diſtreſſed, as well in <hi>England</hi> as <hi>Ireland,</hi> nor the earneſt perſwaſions of their owne diſcouraged, or relenting <hi>party;</hi> nor the frequent <hi>returnes</hi> unto their <hi>alleagiance,</hi> of ſuch
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:155794:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:155794:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:155794:13"/> as are daily <hi>undeceived</hi> amongſt them, If neither the bleeding miſeries actually ruinating in two Kingdomes at <hi>home,</hi> nor the invied dangers threatning from <hi>abroad,</hi> If none of <hi>theſe</hi> can, or if all <hi>theſe,</hi> with our <hi>Religion, Lawes, Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes,</hi> likely to be buried in the aſhes of this <hi>imminent</hi> deſtruction, cannot prevaile one whit upon <hi>theſe</hi> fierce ſpirits, to ſoften their hard and (hitherto) unrelenting hearts, and incline them to thoughts of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Accommodation;</hi> what can the inference amount unto leſſe, then what we promiſed to make good in the beginning? <hi>viz.</hi> That the firebrands of this peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent faction are in a deſperate travaile for the birth of ſome monſtrous deſigne, which cannot be uſhered into the world but by confuſion. We all know whoſe expreſſion it was, <hi>I hate the name of Accommodation;</hi> and the ſpirit of contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and diſſention was not raiſed in them, as they raiſed it in the people, by the conjuration of <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Conspiracies,</hi> (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-ground workes, which no body could diſcover but their owne <hi>Artiſts,</hi> that invented them to imbitter the minds of men againſt His Majeſty.) But all this was the fruit of that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of contention, which they firſt brought with them to the ſervice (though it had proved the disſervice) of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; witneſſe that prodigious <hi>Omen</hi> that long agoe preſaged ourapproaching ruine. When that potent Gentleman put <hi>Moderation</hi> into the Catlogue of his <hi>vices,</hi> he left us to expect nothing elſe but thoſe bitter fruits of <hi>violence,</hi> which we have ſince too ſufficiently taſted.</p>
            <p>Now the ſaid accounts of Warre have taught the people the price of Peace; what, doe they oppoſe to ſtop the current of their ſolicitations? 1. They make ſpeeches in the Houſe, in diſgrace of Peace; and from that <hi>common</hi> ſenſe, a ſenſe muſt be derived unto the whole Kingdome. Till they have ſpilt all the blood of the <hi>ungodly,</hi> or <hi>malignant,</hi> (as they tearme them) they plead an impoſſibility of enjoying peace with her due <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtitures,</hi> as if (becauſe they have begun ſuch a Warre) they could not conclude any other Peace, but what is a ſtranger unto <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe.</hi> The Lord <hi>Brookes</hi> and others have made great uſe of their <hi>talents</hi> this way, to their great honour
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:155794:13"/> amongſt the <hi>bretheren</hi> of the <hi>Separation.</hi> When theſe prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to thruſt peace out of the Houſes, there was anot her plot to cut the <hi>throat</hi> of <hi>it</hi> in the Citie. A multitude (as they had found by long experience) is good at a <hi>dead</hi> lift; and if they be ſet upon't, to have all matters tryed by <hi>club</hi> law, there is no appealing from them. Well! ſuch <hi>forces</hi> muſt be levied as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up their prayers unto both Houſes by an implicite faith in a language they underſtand not thinking any thing a bleſſing that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch a <hi>heavenly</hi> man as Doctor <hi>Burgeſſe</hi> invites them to petition for, and ſo poore <hi>fooles</hi> are earneſt ſuitors to be wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the miſeries of a <hi>civill</hi> warre, from which other <hi>Nations</hi> long to be redeemed. If <hi>ſhame</hi> or <hi>diſcretion,</hi> or <hi>conſcience</hi> makes men backward to this helliſh deſigne then the <hi>Pulpit</hi> muſt be turn'd into a Mount <hi>Ebal,</hi> from whence the <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> of the Houſe of Commons <hi>curſe</hi> them. Leſt ſedition ſhould not <hi>thrive</hi> faſt enough, they ſuborne theſe Preachers, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude them upon (almoſt) every Pariſh, to ſow the ſeeds thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and theſe men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though not of ſo long a ſtanding, have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved their ſtocke of <hi>impudence</hi> beyond the Devill himſelfe. He came whiles the <hi>ſervants</hi> ſlept, but theſe diſperſe their <hi>tares</hi> in the field whiles they looke upon them. Theſe are the <hi>Bellowes</hi> to this fire, the <hi>Trumpets</hi> to this warre, that boggle nor at blaſphemy, to perſwade the people that God is ingaged in their <hi>conspiracy</hi> againſt his <hi>Anointed;</hi> and to this end their prayers are of a more <hi>ſaguine</hi> complexion, then <hi>Eſaus</hi> pottage, Theſe are they that have taken this advantage of ſtirring up the people to ſpoile and <hi>rapine,</hi> that they may (this way) root out a regular Miniſtry, and be planted in their places: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as one of them tells us in his <hi>Plaine Engliſh, He hath a great deale of reaſon to be confident, that ſcarce any conſiderable man</hi> (he ſpeakes of the Clergy) <hi>who hath beene engaged in this quarrell on the Parliament part, if he retaines his integryty,</hi> (he ſhould have changed that word for ſedition) <hi>dares abide the iſſue of a preſent Accommodation.</hi> Certainly there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but their owne <hi>guilt</hi> that ſhould move them to diſtruſt the protection of that <hi>Law</hi> which they have beene bred and borne to. Theſe men can have no fiſhing but in <hi>troubled</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155794:14"/> and therefore when they have done ſweating in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of <hi>Peace</hi> in the Pulpet, they aſſault her in the Preſſe; and in both they have a great advantage: for they wreſtle at liberty, whiles the Champions of <hi>Peace</hi> have their hands tyed behind them. They ſpeake <hi>plaine Engliſh,</hi> whiles the other have their tongues clipt; or if they ſpeake out, are impriſoned: So that <hi>Peace</hi> is firſt awed into <hi>ſilence,</hi> and then by theſe men preſt to death, becauſe ſhe doth not plead to her endightment. Theſe are the inſtruments ſo deſtructive to our peace, ſo indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious in fomenting this execrable Warre. Theſe are the very <hi>Becons,</hi> that (being ſet on fire themſelves) with their prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>blazes</hi> have raiſed ſo many Countries in <hi>Armes,</hi> to their owne ruine, Theſe are the grand <hi>Projectors</hi> to raiſe men and money, making their Miniſtry but a Pander to Rebellion. Their ſtratagemes have beene to awaken them by ſounding this Alarm in their eares: That Gods cauſe, the Proteſtant Religion, Lawes, Liberties, Properties, Priviledges of Parliament, yea their lives, with the lives of their deare wives and children, ly all at the ſtake. They went a ſtep higher in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, perſwading them they were to fight for the defence of the Kings Rights, and to reſcue His Sacred Perſon from the hands of the <hi>Cavaliers;</hi> (ſo in a diſgrace they termed His Majeſties Illuſtrious Nephewes, with the chiefe Nobility and Gentry of the Kingdome) who (as they ſaid) had ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized Him.</p>
            <p>When they were ſupplied with men, (animated by theſe devices) what courſe did they leave unattempted to raiſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to maintaine them? Under the name of the <hi>publike faith</hi> (a cheſt that is bottomeleſſe and inſatiable) they have erected a new <hi>lotterie;</hi> (to cheat our <hi>faith,</hi> and begger the <hi>publike.)</hi> From hence the adventurers were ſure to carry away nothing but <hi>blankes,</hi> the <hi>prizes</hi> being deſigned for themſelves, and the Officers that were neere them; ſome of which are not aſhamed to ſound the Trumpet for it. When the free Contributions were exhauſted from <hi>Voluntiers,</hi> men came to be preſt to theſe prodigall expences. After they had <hi>lent</hi> ſome, they were juſtly paid the <hi>uſe</hi> by having the reſt <hi>taken</hi> from them. Men were
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:155794:14"/> not onely forced to part with their <hi>own,</hi> but to disburſe <hi>others</hi> money alſo, or committed to priſon for their refuſali. This was <hi>I angherne</hi> and <hi>Vivians</hi> caſe, who were committed to <hi>Colche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Goale, for denying to pay 2000l, which was due to the <hi>Prince</hi> from them, and yet the Receiver plundred of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Theſe men are no leſſe carefull for the maintenance of the Kings children then of his Majeſtie, provided it may be done by taking away their Revenues; and thus all the <hi>Rights</hi> as well of King as People, have beene ſecured by an <hi>Antiphraſis</hi> of Parliament. When the Merchants were in diſpute about the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of the Ship called <hi>Sancta Clara,</hi> theſe charitable men (that love no ſtrife betweene brethren) umpir'd in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to reconcile the difference, ſeized upon the goods, which muſt not be redeemed to the uſe of the right owner, under the loane of 20000l. I pray God they have not this trick to comprimiſe all the differences of the Kingdome. To raiſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ney they have robbed both the Church and the Spittle, ſix thouſand pounds being collected for the repairing of S, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes Holborne,</hi> were fetcht away by the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> and others, in the night. If this Church fall, they have inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelves to build God a new houſe in bloud. We reade of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> that he gave all the <hi>ſilver</hi> that was found in the houſe of the Lord to make his peace with a forreigne and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous King: but for ſubjects to take Gods money to wage Warre againſt a pious Prince, we beleeve this may be made one of the firſt precedents; They have not beene more favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the <hi>myſticall</hi> then to the <hi>materiall</hi> Temples of God. A great collection was made for the reliefe of the poore Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants in <hi>London Derry,</hi> and (beſides thoſe vaſt ſummes raiſed by Subſidie for the Armies there) this was all converted to the uſe of this bloudy War, whileſt thoſe our miſerable brethren are ready to periſh (as many that went before them) in their diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. To recompence them from this wrong, they have imployed their Preachers to advance another collection for them; which comming into the ſame hands, we ſuſpect will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed the ſame way. They tooke like care for the diſpoſall of that collection made for <hi>Brainceford,</hi> for the poore of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155794:15"/> Pariſh have not beene a farthing the better for it hitherto, and we beleeve the Spring will have ſo well <hi>recovered</hi> them, that their Phyſitians will thinke it needleſſe to <hi>adminiſter</hi> what was ſo long agoe <hi>provided</hi> for them. Whether theſe men, that would have no ſumme paſſe by their owne <hi>bagge,</hi> care more to relieve the <hi>poore</hi> then <hi>Judus</hi> did, may appeare by diverſe <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances:</hi> amongſt the reſt they brake into the Hoſpitall at <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> and tooke 400l, from them: and a fine device, was lately ſet on foot to raiſe another ſumme. There is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for poore children to be ſent over to get good <hi>breeding</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> a collection muſt be made for them, and this muſt be committed to the hands of their <hi>truſty</hi> and <hi>well-beloved</hi> Alderman <hi>Pennington,</hi> which is like to be imployed to the uſe for which it was pretended, as faithfully as thoſe ſummes ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered for <hi>London Derry</hi> and <hi>Branceford</hi> were.</p>
            <p>Now, leſt the peoples zeale ſhould waſt with their purſes, they keepe them warme by a continuall breathing of reports upon them. If Letters come that ſpeake but upon heare-ſay, they firſt expunge ſo much of the relation as might tend to the diſcouraging of their party, and then publiſh them as the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of ſome great defeat; and (if need be, as there is need enough) they have their <hi>Obſervatour</hi> to write <hi>Commentaries</hi> upon them, leſt the people ſhould miſtake the rare paſſages of Gods providence on their ſide. Another while they declaime againſt the Kings Army as <hi>Popiſh,</hi> (forgetting that their <hi>good wroke</hi> is ſupported by men of any Nation or Religion; and that the Lord <hi>Say</hi> and the Lord <hi>Brookes,</hi> two leading Cards of that faction, have often proteſted they would diſpence with all ſorts of Religions, (though now they make an exception of the true Proteſtant) ſo they might exerciſe their owne freely; and that ſuch a generall Toleration ought to be granted is their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed opinion; and indeed, their <hi>independency</hi> cannot conſiſt otherwiſe, for if I be accountable to none, I will uſe what Religion I pleaſe, without controule.) It hath been well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that when there hath beene any buſineſſe of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to be debated in the Houſes, they have ſtill had the good fortune to be encouraged by the newes of ſome ſtrange
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155794:15"/> ſucceſſe, or exaſperated by ſome great provocation, ſuggeſted by ſuch as made the diſcovery for advantage: But they have beene ſo provident as to lay reports of this nature at a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable diſtance, that they might not be confuted before the preſent turne were ſerved. Thus wee were made beleeve, whileſt His Majeſties Army was in <hi>Yorkeſhore,</hi> and in thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote parts, that they conſiſted of none but <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents;</hi> but this miſt caſt before the peoples eyes to blind them, was ſoone diſpelled by the rayes of our Soveraignes pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as He drew neare us. And however the Earle of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtles</hi> Forces lie all under the ſame ſcandall now, yet as great a cloud as this hath vaniſh'd into nothing; and 'tis poſsible they may draw ſo neare us, that (notwithſtanding their duty and alleagiance have brought ſome <hi>Papiſts</hi> into that Army) we may diſtinctly underſtand, that the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> which they ſay is ſo commonly uſed, will prove no other then the <hi>Booke of Common-Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With theſe jugling and ſlight-of-hand trickes wee have beene long amazed, but they bave beene plaid ſo often over that every man who is not wilfully blinde diſcovers them; and now they ſerve for no uſe but for wiſe men to lament, and boyes to laugh at; we may juſtly wonder what <hi>springs</hi> they move by, that drive them on ſo furiouſly againſt the ſtteame of truth, law, and reaſon: and yet we may ceaſe to wonder, for we have beene ſufficiently informed, that ſome of this vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent party are ſpurr'd on by the law of their owne <hi>neceſſities,</hi> A Captaines pay <hi>per annum</hi> is. More money then five of their prime <hi>Inſtruments</hi> were ever owners of. The <hi>Honeſt Letter</hi> hath told us on which ſide the beggerly Lords and Gentlemen are of; and 'tis eaſily conclude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> conſider who they are that take the preſent pay out of a publike ſtocke, whileſt their <hi>Cure</hi> is ſerved by their under-officers, and who they are that ſerve in their owne perſons; and beſides the hazard of their reſidence raiſe and maintaines Forces at their owne charges. Others we know purſue this deſigne out of an inveterate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice unto Majeſtie. It was an expreſsion of but little loyaltie, (and not the further from truth becauſe uttered in a Taverne)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155794:16"/> that <hi>They would make the King as poore as</hi> Job, <hi>unleſſe he did comply with them.</hi> That Champion that wreſtled to ſtoutly with his Soveraigne at Law, in the caſe of <hi>Ship-money.</hi> might have come off with honour, if he had ſtaid there: But ſeeing him (after ſatisfaction) one of the firſt in the field deſperately provoking His Majeſty to the ſharpe, we ſuſpect malice, though we hope he will be deceived in the length of the Kings weapon, and ſo periſh by it. Others know and have proteſted the King cannot in honour <hi>pardon</hi> them; and if they ſhould ſubmit to the Law, they are too ſure that would prove a <hi>killing</hi> letter to them, and therefore they dare not abide the iſſue of an <hi>Accommodation.</hi> Others having transformed themſelves into Angels of <hi>light,</hi> poſſeſt the people, that they were of a nearer communion, even of the Cabinet-Councell with God himſelfe, and broached their <hi>illuſtions</hi> for divine <hi>Revelations.</hi> Theſe men could ſee, that God had plainly chalked out a way in his holy Word, which our fore-fathers for 1500 yeeres together could never ſee: That Jeſus Chriſt had ſate all this while beſides his <hi>Throne,</hi> and they muſt diſpoſſeſſe <hi>Antichriſt</hi> (whoſe ſpirit and manner of working by lying wonders &amp;c, they are very well acquainted with) before our Saviours government can be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. Theſe men being canoniz'd for Saints by the ignorant multitude, (that underſtand not the depth of <hi>Satans</hi> deluſions) thinke it too great a diſgrace to be <hi>ſtigmatized</hi> with an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious death for Sedition, which they know they are by Law guilty of.</p>
            <p>Thoſe men that began the Warre upon ſuch unwarrantable grounds, and have puruſed it to the murdering of ſo many thouſands, will undoubtedly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ive it (if it be poſſible) to the laſt pinch: For although migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ope they ſhall never compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe differences to their owne perſonall ſafety and preferment, and our irrevocable ſlavery, as one of their <hi>Clerkes</hi> (in his fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous paper) ſaith they may doe; yet they will drive it on as long as they have any hopes to get ſo great a <hi>pawne</hi> into their hands as ſhall inable them to make their owne conditions. If this faile, having ſhipt away ſo much of the <hi>Treaſury</hi> of the Kingdome as may make them conſiderable and welcome gueſts
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:155794:16"/> to <hi>New-England,</hi> or ſuch other places, they care not how miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable they make this Land before they leave it. And her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the way we could wiſh, that our own mony (that was ordered to be tranſported in <hi>Trunkes</hi> without ſearching) might not be brought backe to buy our goods withall; for our ſtocke being plundered by them, if they may have the liberty (as they take liberty to doe any thing) to prize it for themſelves, we may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume they will afford good penny-worths, and never leave us till they have removed both the <hi>Exchanges,</hi> with the Kings <hi>Exchequer</hi> and the <hi>Chamber</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> into the Earle of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wickes</hi> new Liberties. 'Tis time to look about us, for we are to play our <hi>game</hi> with the greateſt <hi>Cheaters</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> who think they have as good a Warrant to ſpoile ſuch as they have call'd <hi>Mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnant,</hi> (for no other reaſon then their loyalty) as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Iſrael</hi> had to ſpoile the <hi>Egyptians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us no longer ſuffer our ſelves to be abuſed, and miſ-led by thoſe falſe lights which they have hung out to deceive us. Doe not all their practices runne <hi>counter</hi> to their pretences? Doe we not perceive them look one way, and ſteere the contrary? Let us learne to know their <hi>aimes,</hi> not by their <hi>words,</hi> but by their <hi>actions.</hi> If we <hi>trace</hi> them through all their <hi>proceedings,</hi> we ſhall find they have given the <hi>lie</hi> to every particular <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,</hi> though never ſo ſpeciouſly alledged for their juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this warre.</p>
            <p>Who was more cryed up then the defence of the true <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Religion? This was the very <hi>ſhield</hi> and <hi>buckler</hi> of their <hi>Army.</hi> This is made the <hi>Generaliſmo</hi> of all their Arguments, and marcheth in the <hi>front</hi> of all the battaile. If this were not at the ſtake, moſt men conclude the warre abſolutely <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi> But how a quarrell can be <hi>juſtly</hi> made to defend a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that condemnes ſuch a <hi>quarrell</hi> and ſuch a <hi>defence,</hi> (as the true <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion doth) I profeſſe I underſtand not. If our Religion did runne an aparent hazard, I am confident this ſcandalous and offenſive defence cannot be juſtified, but by ſuch <hi>Iefuitidall</hi> principles, as all the Schooles of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (except the <hi>Scots,</hi> and not all of them neither, for the Miniſters of <hi>Aberden</hi> have declared themſelves clearly and ſolidly of this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155794:17"/> opinion in their <hi>Duplies)</hi> have unanimouſly exploded. But we have ſufficient grounds of ſuſpition, that the Religion which is ſo barbarouſly militant in a <hi>Buffe-coat,</hi> is not the ſame Religion which was peaceably obedient in a <hi>Surplice.</hi> Wee reade in <hi>Plaine Engliſh</hi> of hopes they have, not onely of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that is, rooting out our <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> but alſo of purging our <hi>Doctrine:</hi> notwithſtanding they have bound themſelves by a ſolemne Proteſtation, (if any ſuch thing can binde them, for they have done as much for the Kings Perſon, Rights and Dignity) to maintaine it. We had thought they would have made their new <hi>experiments</hi> onely upon our old Government; but it ſeemes that wiſe <hi>Colledge</hi> of State-Phyſicians think it fit to make the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our Church their <hi>Patient,</hi> and we are afraid they will let too much bloud there too; and their purge, if they be ſuffered to adminiſter, will be ſtrong enough to overthrow it. Well! whether the maintenance of the true <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Religion be the Argument of this ſword-diſpute, may be decided by a ſpeedy tryall: Let them reduce the <hi>Fabricke</hi> of our Religion according to the <hi>Model</hi> of Queen <hi>Eliſabeths</hi> time, in which thoſe foundations were laid, which made the Church of <hi>England</hi> the moſt eminent and glorious of all <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Churches: If His Majeſty conſents not to all this, and to ſomething more (upon the advice of a grave and learned <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod)</hi> for the ſatisfaction of tender conſciences, but recedeth from His many free and gracious offers to that purpoſe, then let thoſe bitter and ſcandalous imputations of inclining unto <hi>Popery</hi> be never waſht away from Him. But if this be one of the maine Arguments of His Majeſties taking up juſt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and defenſive Armes againſt <hi>Anabaptiſts, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> who have already throwne downe the <hi>hedge,</hi> and now fall to pillaging of the <hi>grapes</hi> of the Lords <hi>Vineyard,</hi> and that with countenance and encouragement from a party in both Houſes; then we may conclude we approach very faſt unto <hi>Atheiſme</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſſe,</hi> and are fallen into thoſe times which Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi> ſpeakes of in his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Word, <hi>B.</hi> 2. <hi>Chapt.</hi> 5. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1. ſpeaking of the care that <hi>Moſes</hi> had of all things that concerned the worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155794:17"/> of God; which care of his all ages have in ſome degree imitated: <hi>Yet</hi> (ſayes he, and we may ſay ſo more truly) <hi>it is now ſo forgotton, and caſt away in this ſuper fine age, by thoſe of the family; By the</hi> Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, <hi>and other</hi> Sectaries, <hi>as all coſt and care beſtowed and had of the Church, wherein God is to he ſerved and worſhipped, is accounted a kind of Popery, and as proceeding from an Idolatrous diſpoſition; inſomuch as time would ſoone bring to paſſe (if it were not reſiſted) that God would be turned out of Churches into Barnes, and from thence againe into the Fields and Mountaines, and under the Hedges; and the offices of the Miniſters (robb'd of all dignity and reſpect) be as contemptible, as theſe places: All Order, Diſcipline, and Church-Government, left to newneſſe of opinion, and mens fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: yea, and ſoone after, as many kindes of Religion would ſpring up, as their are Pariſh Churches within</hi> England: <hi>Every contentious and ignorant perſon clothing his fancy with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and his imagination with the gift of Revelation; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, as when the Truth, which is but one, ſhall appeare to the ſimple multitude, no leſſe variable then contrary to it ſelfe, the faith of men will ſoone after die away by degrees, and alll Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on held in ſcorne and contempt.</hi> Doth not this directly hit the temper of our times, wherein the conformable miniſtry is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally diſcountenanced, ignorant and ſeditious perſons, men of all qualities and profeſſions, ſet up like <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Calves to out-face them? Wherein all ſorts of <hi>Conventicles</hi> (forbidden by Law) are tolerated and frequented by thoſe that ought to puniſh them: wherein men will take upon them to be <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi> and declaime againſt the publike worſhip and ſervice of God, as it hath ſtood ever ſince the Reformation in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſhut up the doores of the <hi>Mother-Church,</hi> (if it bee lawfull to uſe any name of reverence and authority, beſides the name of a <hi>Parliament)</hi> that the ſolemne ſervice of God may not be adminiſtred, as it hath been, for a preſident to other Churches: wherein men are impriſoned and cannot be inlarged, unleſſe they will promiſe to forbeare the uſe of the <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> the <hi>Croſſe</hi> in <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and <hi>kneeling</hi> at the holy <hi>Communion;</hi> wherein the holy Apoſtles of our Saviour
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155794:18"/> are unſainted, as if we now doubted of their ſalvation: all this, and more then this, can be proved againſt Alderman <hi>Penning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> If wee look into the Houſe, leſt their Members ſhould not bee infected faſt enough with this peſtilent <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> the Preachers of their chooſing were for the moſt part notorious, ſchiſmaticall <hi>Separtiſts.</hi> And for the <hi>Synod</hi> (of their owne ſettting forth, after a new tranſlation) for feare the Clergy ſhould have ſent men that were too orthodoxall, they depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them of their rights, (forgetting their Proteſtation, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them to be not the Subjects intended in it) and made choice of as many men as they could get, under no remarkable <hi>character,</hi> but for their ignorant <hi>novelty,</hi> and factious <hi>ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of opinion. If we look upon the men they moſt confide in, we ſhall find them of the ſame ſtampe, or elſe their priſoners muſt not be committed to them. Doctor <hi>Leyton</hi> an old <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Preacher, ſtigmatized long ſince for Sedition, Gaoler at <hi>Lambeth Houſe. Dillingham</hi> a notorious Browniſt, with his wife and family, Goaler at <hi>London-Houſe. Deveniſh</hi> the Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and <hi>Randall</hi> the Porter, both <hi>Conventicle-Preachers,</hi> at <hi>Wincheſter-Houſe:</hi> and the Porter at <hi>Ely-Houſe</hi> can deliver as much extemporary Sedition as the beſt of them. If we look into their Army, wee ſhall find their intemperate zeale (not without encouragement from ſome great ones) hath tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, not onely to the prophanation of Churches, defacing of Monuments, tearing of holy Books, and decent Veſt ments, but even to the murdering of the true ſonnes of the Church for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyning in her devotions, as the late example at <hi>Lambeth</hi> evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denceth.</p>
            <p>Wee ſee then what is done for the defence of the true <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Religion, as it ſtands reformed and eſtabliſht in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> This Religion is pretended, but another is practiced; and in order to this <hi>new</hi> one, (for the old hath conſiſted with the old government) <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> muſt be rooted out: and to this end, they have uſed the moſt Reverend <hi>Biſhops,</hi> (for no other crime then for being of that function) as whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lome the enemies of the Goſpell did the holy Martyrs of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> when they clothed them in the skins of wilde beaſts,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:155794:18"/> to animate the dogges to teare them: ſo the Fathers of the Church have been ſet forth under the moſt ſcandalous and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious character, to inrage the people againſt them. And although they are as farre from diſcovering, as from agreeing what they would have in the roome of it, yet this muſt downe, that's concluded; and though a <hi>Synod</hi> be deſired, as the moſt competent Judge of ſuch Controverſies, yet this is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened onely for colour fake; the work muſt be <hi>done,</hi> or rather <hi>undone,</hi> before they be conſulted with, or aſſembled. We may expoſtulate, though they will not allow their <hi>Votes,</hi> how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable ſoever, to be diſputed. How came <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> that hath ſtood ſo long a <hi>piller</hi> in the houſe of God, to grow ſo dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrically oppoſite to the truth or peace of the Goſpell? Was not our Religion reformed under that Government, and hath not our Church and State flouriſh't (to the envy of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours) under it? If ſome <hi>tares</hi> have ſprung up under it, have they not ſprung up much faſter, and ſpread further under other formes of Government beyond the Seas? If inconveniences have crept in through that <hi>wall,</hi> which, if not of <hi>Chriſts</hi> own, is doubtleſſe of his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> building: much more through thoſe low <hi>hedges</hi> of their ſetting up, who hhve no grounds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their owne fancies to plant them on. There is a neceſſity of emerging <hi>offences,</hi> and <hi>tares</hi> will grow amongſt the <hi>Wheat</hi> untill the Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>veſt, or elſe our Saviour hath deceived us. His wiſdome ſees, that the very chaffe may contribute ſomething to the benefit of the good <hi>graine</hi> in this life, and therefore hath reſerved the thorow-purging of his <hi>floore</hi> till his owne comming unto Judgement. A little breaking in of the <hi>ſalt</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters makes our helds more fruitfull: Our chief care muſt be to keep out <hi>Inundations,</hi> and the way to doe that is to keep the bankes up and to keepe them ſound, not to <hi>levell</hi> them.</p>
            <p>The Houſes did once thinke it convenient to declare by <hi>Votes</hi> (which we ſee <hi>religiouſly</hi> obſerv'd in other things) that they intended the aboliſhing, neither of the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> nor of the <hi>Church-Goverument:</hi> And truely if wee perceive <hi>Votes</hi> (which have preſum'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o challenge ſo much reſpect and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration from us) created onely to ſerve turnes upon occaſion,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:155794:19"/> and carried <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> as emergent advantages are admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, they will preſently loſe their reputation (amongſt us) of being infallible, and gives us hopes, that upon the more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation of ſecond thoughts, at leaſt all groundleſſe <hi>Votes,</hi> apparently and experimentally d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtructive to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſhall bee recalled. And for the Government of the Church (being purg'd of ſome abuſes) wee profeſſe wee like the Preachers advice ſo well, and have found their <hi>principles</hi> ſo peſtilent, that we would not willingly meddle with them that are given to <hi>change,</hi> unleſſe we can ſee better Arguments produced (though this laſt of the ſword hath been the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt) to move us. We are of their opinion, that having dranke <hi>old</hi> Wine, cannot deſire <hi>new,</hi> for they know the <hi>old</hi> is better. And it is not an idle obſervation, that ſince they fell from <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> to <hi>rooting</hi> up, their endeavours have been almoſt miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly blaſted, by an immediate and remarkeable curſe upon them.</p>
            <p>If there be any that thinks this order in the Church is not worth the ſtrife about it, and that our Religion may conſiſt without it, let them with a ſad and ſerious heart ponder theſe Conſiderations. 1. That inſtead of theſe, by the <hi>independent</hi> way, a Pope, and however, a Biſhop will be ſet up in every Pariſh. 2. That there was no other Government (though perhaps ſome other qualifications in it) heard of in the Church of God, till about 100 yeares ſince, inſomuch as ſome (of no ſmall note for learning and piety) ſtand in great doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there can be any lawfull <hi>Ordination,</hi> and conſequently any lawfull <hi>Miniſtry</hi> without it. Theſe (who make up a farre more conſiderable party in this Church, then thoſe who have already ſeparated, and therefore ought in the firſt place by all the rules of Chriſtian charity, to have their ſcruples ſatisfied) upon the <hi>rooting</hi> out of this <hi>Ancient</hi> Government, muſt needs abandon our Communion. 3. That the true <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion eſtabliſht in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> was never ſo much undermin'd and blemiſht whileſt ſome of the Biſhops <hi>ſlept;</hi> and others were too <hi>active,</hi> as it hath been by new ſprung up <hi>Sects,</hi> and <hi>monſtrous</hi> opinions, ſince their office was ſuſpended.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:155794:19"/> 4. That the next <hi>Orders</hi> like to be quarrel'd at (if it be not too evident they are quarrel'd at already) will be the <hi>Nobility</hi> and the <hi>Gentry;</hi> and if we ſhould allow the argument againſt the <hi>Order</hi> of Biſhops, that the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, and the generall ſafety of the Kingdome may conſiſt without them: may not the ſame argument with as good reaſon be taken up againſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the meaner ſort of people (who ſhall have hopes to ſhare their eſtates amongſt them) till all degrees be levelled? Laſtly, That the argument of the diſpute is not ſo much, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhops, or no Biſhops; as whether a King, or no King: for we muſt hold the <hi>negative,</hi> if Subjects may be allowed by force of Armes, when they cannot get the Kings conſent, to pull downe any piece of his ſettled Government.</p>
            <p>With the Fathers they pretend to thruſt out the Children and thoſe are commonly deciphered under the notion of <hi>ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous</hi> Miniſters. The truth is, it were well for the Church of God, if all that were ſuch were thruſt out of her boſome: But they have ſtretcht the Word to ſuch a latitude, that if they ſhould goe on, there would ſcarce be found an Orthodox man in the Kingdome out of this <hi>Catalogue.</hi> For there are a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>ſcorners</hi> and <hi>terrible ones, That watch for iniquitie, that make a man an offender for a word, and lay a ſnare for him that reproveth in the gate, and turne aſide the juſt for a thing of nought, Iſa.</hi> 29. 20, 21. Is hee loyall according to the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of divers oaths ſundry times repeated by him? He is a ſcandalous Miniſter. Is he a man well affected to the preſent Government, &amp;c. or to peace? he is a dangerous man, and ſcandalous. In the <hi>interim</hi> they ſet up their railing <hi>Rabſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaes,</hi> that <hi>blaspheme</hi> God, and <hi>ſlander</hi> the footſteps of his Annointed in ſuch ſort, as their Prayers and Preaching are a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſcandall, (except enmities, ſeditions, reviling of Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Miniſters, when practiſed by them, with the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of a party in both Houſes ceaſe to be workes of the fleſh.) If we ſhould forme compariſons, wee ſhould find <hi>moates</hi> in ſome mens eyes, made greater by the multiplying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glaſſe of malice, (which they make too much uſe of) then the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eames,</hi> that are moſt conſpicuous in the eyes of others. In
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:155794:20"/> ſome men they perſecute their humane frailties and indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whilſt they protect others, whoſe offences are died in <hi>graine.</hi> Maſter <hi>Pigott</hi> (amongſt other ſuch like <hi>Articles)</hi> was accuſed by ſome few ſeditious men of the Pariſh of S. <hi>Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres,</hi> for drinking a Beere glaſſe of <hi>White-wine,</hi> with a <hi>Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and <hi>Sugar:</hi> and though vindicated by the teſtimony of 600 of the ableſt men, had his reputation blaſted (with no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to his witneſſes) by Maſter <hi>Corbet,</hi> who ſate then in the chaire of <hi>Examinations,?</hi> I had like to have called it the ſeat of the ſcornfull) and gave his hand afterwards that he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to exerciſe his Miniſtry, by which meanes he hath ſince been put by two <hi>Lectures,</hi> at <hi>Alhallowes Berking,</hi> and <hi>Broad-ſtreet.</hi> I make no queſtion they have met with ſome ſcandalous enough: I doe not excuſe them. But others they have proſecuted, whom they might with much more honour have acquitted, and given a checke to their too officious and troubleſome neighbours. Look we upon ſuch as are in moſt favour and eſteem with them, we ſhall find they have trode their ſhooes <hi>awry,</hi> aſwell as others. We may ſet Doctor <hi>Burgeſſe</hi> in the <hi>front,</hi> and becauſe he was ſo <hi>buſie</hi> to pick holes in the coates of his <hi>brethren,</hi> and rackt up, the very <hi>aſhes</hi> of the dead to diſcover their corruptions, we ſhall be the bolder to remember him, not only of a man that was a <hi>Pluraliſt,</hi> but of one that the <hi>High-Commiſſion</hi> looked upon for <hi>Adultery;</hi> And of one that with continuall <hi>ſuites</hi> of Law vext two Pariſhes and muſt have been <hi>calculated</hi> in the <hi>Black-bill,</hi> if he had not taken himſelfe off by his good ſervice againſt Biſhops. Doctor <hi>Downing</hi> a reputed <hi>weathercock,</hi> that turns which way ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the wind of his owne humour, or ambition blowes him; ſometimes a great <hi>ſuitor</hi> to be the Earle of <hi>Straffords</hi> Chaplaine, thinking that the readieſt way to a <hi>Biſhoprick;</hi> and whilſt he had hopes of the preferment, writ ſtoutly in juſtification of that <hi>calling,</hi> Maſter <hi>Calamy,</hi> another great <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> of the <hi>new</hi> way, ſometimes complyed with Biſhop <hi>Wren,</hi> preached frequently in his <hi>ſurplice</hi> and <hi>Hood,</hi> read Prayers at the <hi>Railes,</hi> bowed at the name of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and undertook to ſatisfie and to reduce ſuch as <hi>ſcupled</hi> at theſe <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> inſomuch as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:155794:20"/> the Earle of <hi>Warwicke</hi> ſaid, <hi>He would be loſt if he were not taken off,</hi> and ſo removed him to a living in <hi>Eſſex.</hi> This was all the <hi>Phyſick</hi> that was given him, to <hi>purge</hi> him from that which he now ſtiles <hi>Superſtition,</hi> though it was never ſo before he left it. Maſter <hi>Harding</hi> another great <hi>Apoſtle</hi> for that <hi>way,</hi> if he had not ſecured himſelfe by complying with that <hi>faction,</hi> had been complained of for his <hi>vicious</hi> life, being a notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fornicatour, often taken by the <hi>Watch</hi> in a diſguiſe with <hi>Harlots;</hi> and ſince hee ingaged himſelfe for the <hi>good</hi> work, attempted a rape upon a <hi>Vintners</hi> wife in <hi>Southwarke;</hi> yet he hath made up all theſe <hi>breaches</hi> in his life, by making a greater in the Church. Maſter <hi>Bridge</hi> of <hi>Norwich</hi> being called to an account by the Biſhop (as we are credibly informed) for keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing another mans <hi>wife,</hi> left his <hi>Cure,</hi> and then pretended he was <hi>driven</hi> away, becauſe he would not ſubmit to <hi>Innovations.</hi> Maſter <hi>Goodwin</hi> of <hi>Coleman-ſtreet</hi> in great eſteem amongſt ſome of them, yet (let him ſpin his opinion into never ſo fine a thred) a <hi>Socinian.</hi> Maſter <hi>John Sedgewicke</hi> of <hi>London-wall,</hi> a <hi>ſimoniacke</hi> and <hi>perjur'd,</hi> both upon <hi>Record.</hi> And every one hath heard of that light and prophane ſpeech of M. <hi>Evans,</hi> that hee did <hi>breake</hi> the poore womens hearts with preaching of damnation, and carried the <hi>pieces</hi> in his pocket. And (if wee may touch the <hi>apple</hi> of their eye) we have heard (for our eyes are not every where to ſee them) that Maſter <hi>Marſhall</hi> hath a powerfull faculty of perſwaſion with the weaker <hi>ſex,</hi> (and all <hi>ſeducers</hi> after their <hi>old</hi> maſter goe that way) to draw the affections, and then the eſtates from brothers children unto his owne. By theſe <hi>inſtances</hi> it is evident, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their zeale for a <hi>thorow</hi> reformation, they can diſpenſe with <hi>offences,</hi> aſwell in the <hi>Clergy</hi> as in the <hi>Laity,</hi> if they will become ſerviceable unto the preſent <hi>deſigne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another thing pretended to be reformed in the <hi>Church,</hi> was <hi>Pluralities</hi> and <hi>Non-reſidence;</hi> and this was not ſo much, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they thought theſe things unlawfull, as to make roome for their owne <hi>Emiſſaries.</hi> Who would think that men, who have <hi>voted</hi> it a thing unlawfull and unconſcionable to hold <hi>two</hi> Livings, or but <hi>one</hi> and not <hi>reſide</hi> upon it, ſhould practice
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:155794:21"/> it themſelves. Nothing hath been cry'd downe more by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> ſince the ſitting of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> and yet we find many late <hi>examples</hi> of their owne making. Maſter <hi>Goodricke</hi> of little <hi>Houghton</hi> hath been taken from his <hi>reſidence</hi> at his Cure, and made Lecturer at <hi>Tottenham,</hi> by the meanes of Sir <hi>Edward Barkeham</hi> and Maſter <hi>Stroude.</hi> Maſter <hi>Theodor Graves</hi> Parſon of great <hi>Linford,</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks,</hi> made <hi>non-reſident</hi> by an <hi>Order</hi> of Parliament. Maſter <hi>George Horiford</hi> of <hi>Stutsbury,</hi> in the Dioceſſe of <hi>Peterborough,</hi> made Vicar of <hi>Banbury</hi> by the Lord <hi>Say;</hi> it ſeems his <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> can diſpenſe with a double <hi>Benefice</hi> in his own Chaplains. Doctor <hi>Wincop</hi> (whoſe new preferment hath made him forget ſome of his old principles) though he had the <hi>fleece</hi> of a good flock before, the Houſe of Commons hath given him <hi>Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Induction</hi> into Doctor <hi>Brayes</hi> living, S. <hi>Martines</hi> in the fields; but whether they can <hi>vote</hi> him into the <hi>profits,</hi> as they have done into the <hi>paines,</hi> is doubtfull. Many other <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts</hi> have been made this <hi>Parliament,</hi> (and ſome ſince the Bill was drawne up againſt them.) Maſter <hi>Henry Trewman,</hi> Rector of <hi>Cornwall</hi> and <hi>Newarke,</hi> by the Earle of <hi>Clare.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Tho: Caril</hi> of <hi>Slindon</hi> and <hi>Harting,</hi> by the Lord <hi>Saint-Iohns.</hi> Maſter <hi>Iohn Dixon</hi> of <hi>Glenfold</hi> and <hi>Baynes,</hi> by the Lord <hi>Haſtings.</hi> Who can think that theſe men were in <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt,</hi> and not rather upon <hi>deſigne,</hi> when they cry'd out ſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly againſt <hi>Pluralities?</hi> We would faine know what gift of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquity</hi> hath been <hi>voted</hi> into Maſter <hi>Marſhall,</hi> that he ſhould be able to officiate at S. <hi>Margaret Weſtminſter, Windſor,</hi> or any where, and yet not neglect his Cure at <hi>Finchinfield</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi> Maſter <hi>Caſe</hi> officiates at <hi>London,</hi> and leaves his Cure in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> to be ſupply'd by <hi>Rawbone</hi> an illiterate Lay-man.</p>
            <p>Another thing pretended for the <hi>advancement</hi> of Religion, was the eſtabliſhing of a <hi>Preaching</hi> Miniſtry throughout the Kingdome. Certainly a very <hi>pious</hi> work, if <hi>Orthodox</hi> men be planted in all <hi>Pariſhes:</hi> But if ſuch be rooted out as are of <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt</hi> parts to inſtruct, and men of <hi>desperate</hi> principles and <hi>facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> ſpirits thruſt into their places; this (as by too wofull an experience is now made evident) will prove deſtructive both
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:155794:21"/> to <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> Yet this is the <hi>great</hi> work for which way muſt be made (ſaith the Authour of <hi>Plaine En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh) by diſplacing idle, ſcandalous, ſuperſtitious, ignorant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:</hi> And how muſt theſe be diſplaced? Why ſaith he, <hi>If this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage against them of ſtirring up the people to ſpoile and rapine were taken, it were a good likely meanes</hi> (very warrantable and honeſt meanes ſurely, according to <hi>Wat Tylers</hi> and <hi>Iacke Strawes</hi> Doctrine) <hi>of rooting out them who had ſhuffled their Cards ſo cunningly, as to be out of the reach of the Law in other reſpects.</hi> This puts me in mind of that which Colonell <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> ſaid to Maſter <hi>Gatford</hi> at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> (when he took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his <hi>book</hi> out of the Preſſe, for ſpeaking for obedience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> againſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts:)</hi> He told him he had been a great <hi>oppoſer</hi> of the Archbiſhops <hi>Innovations,</hi> but car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried himſelfe ſo <hi>cunningly,</hi> that the <hi>Law</hi> could not lay hold up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and ſo (he told him) he had behaved himſelfe now; (in oppoſition to the <hi>Anabaptiſts)</hi> but though the <hi>Law</hi> could not lay hold upon him, they had a <hi>power</hi> could reach him; and this was the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Dragooneers,</hi> which brought him up a Priſoner forthwith to <hi>Ely-Houſe.</hi> The truth is, what ever they ſay, their aime is not ſo much at the <hi>idle</hi> and <hi>ignorant,</hi> for the one <hi>winkes</hi> at all their <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>odious</hi> principles, and the other <hi>concurre</hi> with them in the practice of <hi>them.</hi> Their chiefe envy is at the moſt learned and moſt painfull Preachers (if they keep not ſilence at their faction.) Why is the Lord Primate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Morton,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Prideaux,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Brownrigg,</hi> Doctor <hi>Hildſworth,</hi> Doctor <hi>Featly,</hi> Maſter <hi>Shute,</hi> and others of <hi>ſingular</hi> learning and piety, under a <hi>cloud</hi> with them, and ſome of them <hi>ordered</hi> to be impriſoned? Why are ſo many Priſons full of men that are Preachers, as well by their <hi>Examples</hi> as their <hi>Sermons?</hi> Maſter <hi>Squire,</hi> Maſter <hi>Stone,</hi> Maſter <hi>Swadlin,</hi> that are ſcarce allowed <hi>ſtraw</hi> to lie on, (whileſt His Majeſty is exclaim'd againſt, when he affords <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> better uſage.) Maſter <hi>Reading</hi> of <hi>Dover,</hi> Maſter <hi>Griffith</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Maſter <hi>Ingoldsby</hi> of <hi>Watton</hi> in <hi>Hartfordſhire,</hi> Maſter <hi>Wilcocks</hi> of <hi>Goudhurſt</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi> Theſe, and many others, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done nothing worthy of <hi>death,</hi> or of <hi>bonds,</hi> are inſerted
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:155794:22"/> into the <hi>black</hi> bill of <hi>ſcandalous</hi> and <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> Miniſters, for preaching nothing but <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>Soveraigne</hi> Authority, and <hi>points</hi> conſonant to the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and the <hi>Doctrine of the Church of England,</hi> as it ſtands eſtabliſhed by <hi>Act</hi> of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. I confeſſe Maſter <hi>Ingoldsby</hi> aggravated his <hi>crime</hi> of preaching for obedience, by ſetting forth the Doctrine of our Church (in ſix <hi>Homilies</hi> eſtabliſhed by Parliament, for the uſe of every <hi>Pariſh)</hi> againſt <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and the oathes of <hi>Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> and <hi>Allegeance,</hi> with the <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> and an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> prefixt to light the <hi>people</hi> unto their duty; for which he was ſent for up (the ſecond time) with a <hi>Troope</hi> of <hi>Horſe:</hi> but eſcaping from them, he came of his owne <hi>accord</hi> to his <hi>priſon,</hi> deſirous to make his <hi>anſwer,</hi> which they find no leiſure yet to hearken to. Nay, they will not permit that holy man Maſter <hi>Thruſh-croſſe,</hi> to teach <hi>White-Hall</hi> to continue <hi>loyall,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> He ſeem'd to taske the Juſtice of this <hi>bloudy</hi> Warre, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon this <hi>new</hi> deſigne, and preſently an <hi>inquiſition</hi> is made after him, and the <hi>Sunday</hi> following a <hi>Guard</hi> is ſet upon every Gate, (if not for other malicious ends likewiſe) to fright him from the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> This is their account of <hi>ſcandalous</hi> Miniſters, whom they would have, either <hi>rooted out,</hi> or <hi>ſilenced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another <hi>project</hi> to advance <hi>Religion</hi> was, the taking the <hi>Clergy</hi> off from <hi>Temporall</hi> imployments; and this is ſtretcht ſo farre, that they are reputed <hi>Excentrickes,</hi> as moving out of the <hi>ſphere</hi> of their calling, if they ſtudy to preach downe <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>diſobedience.</hi> And yet all the world knowes, their owne <hi>Clergy</hi> have been as active <hi>inſtruments</hi> here, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Henderſon</hi> in the State affaires of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Doctor <hi>Burgeſſe</hi> (we find him at every turne) and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn Sedgewicke,</hi> muſt be made Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of a <hi>Sub-Committee,</hi> for advancement of monies. Nay, the <hi>Doctsr</hi> (who hath obtained the Title of a <hi>Colonell</hi> this <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Commencement,</hi> for riding to encourage the work, with his caſe of Piſtols) was ſo officious as to aſſiſt <hi>Plundering</hi> at the <hi>Globe</hi> Taverne in <hi>Holborne.</hi> And there is not a deſigne, but <hi>theſe</hi> men have a <hi>finger</hi> in it, and of their tongues more then their ſhare.</p>
            <p>Wee have ſeen how faithfull they have fought for the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:155794:22"/> Church: they promiſed and proteſted they did as much (and they have done no leſſe) for the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdome.</hi> That this warre was for the defence of the Kings <hi>Perſon</hi> is ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence as honeſt men are aſhamed of, and all men laugh at, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you can perſwade them, you teach your bullets to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh as nicely as your ſelves, between the Kings <hi>Perſonall</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and his <hi>Perſon.</hi> Thoſe that have heard it delivered for ſound doctrine (and without controll) that the King might have been killed in the <hi>crowd</hi> with a good Conſcience, and have ſeen what <hi>Regiments</hi> and <hi>Troops</hi> were moſt aimed at (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Captaine <hi>Blagues</hi> directions) at <hi>Keinton</hi> battell, and heard the bullets ſing about His Majeſties eares, cannot believe you did more then complement, when you ſtiled His royall perſon <hi>Sacred;</hi> unleſſe you can change the property of <hi>Sacred</hi> Perſons, as well as of <hi>Sacred</hi> things, which you goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout (though all men account it <hi>Sacriledge)</hi> to <hi>alienate.</hi> And how ſhould wee believe you would fight for the defence of His <hi>Perſon,</hi> when you ſeize upon all His proviſion, that if you cannot do it by the <hi>ſword,</hi> you may murder him by <hi>famine?</hi> But admit they fight not for the defence of his royall perſon, yet they may fight for his <hi>Crowne</hi> and <hi>Dignity:</hi> this hath been much pretended to, and that they did ſo in ſome ſence, may very well be believed. But in earneſt, how can we be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded they tender the <hi>Honour</hi> of the Crowne, when they imploy their <hi>Rabbies</hi> to ſatisfie (if it were poſſible) mens conſciences in a wilfull and groundleſſe diſobedience, by returning ill lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages to ſober and ſolid arguments againſt it? How doe they maintaine <hi>Prerogative,</hi> when they pretend to a power <hi>Coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> with their Soveraigne, and ſet up men to cleare the Title for them, though they have no <hi>evidence,</hi> but ſuch as was never ſeen by our wiſe <hi>Anceſtours?</hi> The very name of <hi>Monarch</hi> implies a <hi>ſoleſhip</hi> of Government, to them that underſtand it. If the <hi>Monarchy</hi> be mixt, 'tis not ſo, as if the Soveraignty were ſhared amongſt <hi>diverſe,</hi> for that were a meer <hi>Bull:</hi> But this mixture conſiſts of theſe two <hi>ingredients,</hi> viz. <hi>ſetled</hi> law, and (where a law is not ſetled) the <hi>diſcretion</hi> and <hi>prudence</hi> of the Governour. In making lawes (wherein their chiefe power
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:155794:23"/> conſiſteth) they may propound and conſent, but it lies ſtill in the Kings power to refuſe, or ratifie. If the power of the <hi>three</hi> Eſtates be <hi>Coordinate,</hi> and the rule hold (as the <hi>Fuller anſwer</hi> will have it) <hi>Coordinata ſe invicem ſupplent,</hi> Coordinates ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply one another, he preſently brings the <hi>three</hi> Eſtates into the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons</hi> (and they delegate the power to a cloſe Committee) and ſo makes them a Court of <hi>Record</hi> to give <hi>oath, commit,</hi> and <hi>ſentence</hi> at their pleaſure (as they have done too many) and every <hi>Vote</hi> of theirs (though the King and the Lords diſſent from it) by vertue of this power of <hi>Supplying</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in them, ſhall be made an <hi>Act</hi> of Parliament. And if the King be brought thus low, ſhall he ſtand there? ſhall he not from <hi>Coordinate</hi> be brought a ſtep lower, and be made <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate?</hi> why, yes, that is another <hi>Doctrine,</hi> He is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis minor,</hi> a Subject to all his Subjects; and thoſe <hi>miſtakes,</hi> which were ſo often condemned as breaches of their <hi>priviledge,</hi> were nothing elſe but ſo many acts of His Majeſties <hi>diſobedience.</hi> And His people being <hi>greater</hi> then hee, and <hi>above</hi> him, may take his owne <hi>Forts</hi> and <hi>Armes,</hi> to <hi>reduce</hi> and <hi>compell</hi> him. Was there ever any <hi>Ieſuite</hi> out-went them in defending the <hi>rights</hi> of Kings? Some are ſo tender of His Majeſties Crowne, that they are not aſhamed to ſay, the oath of <hi>Alleagiance</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver made to bind the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> but the <hi>Papiſts</hi> onely.</p>
            <p>If they fight not for the rights of the <hi>Crowne,</hi> perhaps they fight for the rights of <hi>Parliament.</hi> That hath been preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded too, yet who ever broke the <hi>Priviledges</hi> thereof more, then tumults of their own countenancing and raiſing? The <hi>carriages</hi> which themſelves onely have managed, have brought <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> under ſo much prejudice and diſparagement, that the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony of a due reverence, will be as much denyed unto them as unto any thing elſe, till ſome other courſe be taken to reſtore them to their <hi>Ancient</hi> reputation.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Plea</hi> for the <hi>Lawes</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> is no leſſe vaine: for if they had any Law for their proceedings, there ſhould bee no need of ſo many ſtrange <hi>wilde,</hi> and <hi>never-before-heard of Ordinances.</hi> Inſomuch as the <hi>Contra-Replicant</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth on their behalfe, in this manner. <hi>Nothing has done us</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:155794:23"/> 
               <hi>more harme of late, then this opinion of adhering to law onely for our preſervation. It would be good to adde more (arbitrary) power to the Earle of</hi> Eſſex <hi>for</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>till I ſee him look't upon and ſerved as a temporary</hi> Dictator, <hi>and the bounds of his Commiſſion to be onely thus;</hi> Ne quid detrimenti capiat Reſpub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica cavere: <hi>I ſhall never think the Parliaments ſafety ſufficiently provided for.</hi> The <hi>Law</hi> then is not the thing you fight for, for you fight againſt it: And the <hi>Judges</hi> ſit in the Houſe for <hi>Ciphers,</hi> as the <hi>Clergy</hi> in the Convocation.</p>
            <p>Doe you fight to maintain the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Subject? Indeed you ſtand deeply ingaged to doe your beſt for <hi>that;</hi> for it was never ſo infringed ſince the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> as it hath been by your ſelves ſince you have taken the charge of the <hi>Militia.</hi> If we cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate the number of <hi>Priſoners,</hi> who have been committed this yeare, we ſhall find <hi>hundreds</hi> reſtrained of their <hi>liberty</hi> moſt unjuſtly; for Maſter <hi>Pym</hi> told us in the name, and as the <hi>ſence</hi> of both Houſes (in that ſpeech at <hi>Guild-Hall) That it is againſt the rules of juſtice, that any men ſhould be impriſoned upon a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall charge, when no particulars are proved againſt them;</hi> and yet we know no particulars were proved or alleaged againſt the Lord of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> the Lord of <hi>Portland,</hi> &amp;c. How many men petitioning for inlargement, when no <hi>charge</hi> could bee brought againſt them, have notwithſtanding been detained in priſon, becauſe they had not contributed to the maintenance of the warre? And if it be ſo farre from truth, that any <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars</hi> have been proved, that not ſo much as a generall <hi>charge</hi> hath been produced, then either Maſter <hi>Pym</hi> in the name of the Houſe abuſes the ſence of the Houſe, or elſe thir impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment is againſt the <hi>rules of juſtice.</hi> But perhaps theſe <hi>rules</hi> of juſtice are made in favour of <hi>Iſaas Pennington,</hi> and his three fellow-Citizens, <hi>Kimbolton,</hi> and the <hi>five members.</hi> Such men as <hi>theſe,</hi> that are members of the Houſe, or engaged in their ſervice, <hi>theſe</hi> men may not be impriſoned upon a <hi>generall</hi> charge, though it be a charge of <hi>High Treaſon.</hi> And yet I muſt tell you, if this be a true <hi>maxime</hi> of State, it is the greateſt <hi>Soloeciſme</hi> that can be imagined, and I am ſure, contrary to the practice of all <hi>Indiciall</hi> proceedings upon <hi>criminall</hi> cauſes;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:155794:24"/> For if there ſhould be no impriſonment upon a <hi>generall</hi> charge before particulars are proved, then there can be no Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before ſome kind of <hi>tryall,</hi> and a <hi>Conſtable</hi> could not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend a <hi>felon,</hi> (though he had a warrant for it) without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending againſt the <hi>rules</hi> of Juſtice; for his apprehenſion is an impriſonment, and yet no <hi>particulars</hi> proved; which ſayes M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Pym,</hi> ſpeaking the ſence of both Houſes) is againſt the <hi>rules</hi> of Juſtice. Well! if ſuch an impriſonment be againſt the <hi>rules</hi> of Juſtice, we are taught from the priſons, the way to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſteſt <hi>Court</hi> extant. And if thoſe <hi>rules</hi> had been as well obſerved on the behalfe of <hi>all</hi> His Majeſties good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, as they have been ſoundly preached to <hi>ſome</hi> of them, there had not been that need (as wee ſee there is) of a <hi>Month<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> conſecration of new priſons. But perhaps the ſence of the Houſe is, that the <hi>King</hi> cannot commit to priſon upon a <hi>generall</hi> charge, when no particulars are proved (His Majeſties power hath been cut very ſhort of late.) But the Houſes being more <hi>indulgent</hi> to their owne priviledges, may <hi>Carve</hi> themſelves a power of a greater latitude (and they have carved themſelves very freely of the prerogative of the Crowne) and as occaſion ſerve declare and uſe it. They may commit upon a <hi>due infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> without any proofe of particulars. (and this is a new created priviledge of the Houſe of Commons, which hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could commit none but their owne Members) Maſter <hi>Pym</hi> in his ſaid ſpeech declares the practice of the Houſe, <hi>That they never have committed any man, but ſuch men as by due in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> (and perhaps not ſo due neither) <hi>they conceived to be ſeditious perſons, and like to trouble the peace of the State.</hi> What I againſt the rules of Juſtice to impriſon any men upon a <hi>generall</hi> charge (though of high treaſon) when no <hi>particulars</hi> are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and in his <hi>next</hi> obſervation but one, men committed upon <hi>Informations</hi> and <hi>conceipts?</hi> what is become of the <hi>rules</hi> of juſtice now? or what is become of the <hi>Gentlemans</hi> memory? If he hath forgot his owne <hi>rules</hi> of Juſtice ſo ſuddenly, we may ceaſe to wonder, that he hath forgot the <hi>rule</hi> of our law, which he ſo much magnified in his ſpeech upon the <hi>Attainder</hi> of the Earle of <hi>Strafford.</hi> But what! have they committed no man
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:155794:24"/> but ſuch as by <hi>due information</hi> they conceived ſeditious? I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve none but ſuch as they <hi>conceived</hi> ſeditious. <hi>Conceit</hi> doth much: and if they <hi>conceive</hi> a man ſo, they never <hi>travaile</hi> long, before their <hi>Sergeant</hi> playes the Midwife, and aſſiſts them to bring him forth <hi>ſuch</hi> as they had conceived him to be. But we much doubt, whether this were alwaies by due informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for we know ſome, that after three weeks impriſonment (and no hearing) put in baile, and within a forthnight returned out of the Countrey, continued in priſon a good while longer; and at laſt, the information was found ſo <hi>undue,</hi> that they were diſmiſſed. And we have ſeen an Order under Maſter <hi>Lawrence Whitakers</hi> hand, that ſuch <hi>Gentlemen</hi> ſhould be moved to bring in the <hi>accuſation</hi> againſt ſuch priſoners; and if none could be found, that then they might be diſcharged. When the high <hi>Sheriffe</hi> of <hi>Eſſex</hi> pleaded, he had done nothing; (knowing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence was wont to be a faire excuſe) the <hi>Speaker</hi> told him, They did commit him for <hi>prevention.</hi> Where is the <hi>due infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> now, upon which priſoners are committed? Nay, theſe great <hi>Aſſertors</hi> of the ſubjects <hi>liberty,</hi> have reſtrained the <hi>gray</hi> haires to their great hazard. Alderman <hi>Backhouſe,</hi> not ſo rich as honeſt. And Archdeacon <hi>Hilliar,</hi> though above 80. yeares of age, and ſo infirme, that he had been a long time bed-rid, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to pay down 800. <hi rend="sup">l</hi>. was carried five miles from <hi>Exceter</hi> to be ſhipt away, to the endangering of his life. And Sir <hi>George Whitmore,</hi> very aged, was ſhipt away for <hi>Yarmouth,</hi> and could not have the liberty of a <hi>Coach</hi> for his health, though he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be at the charge of any <hi>guard</hi> they ſhould think fit to ſend down with him. Have not ſome Parliament men come upon the <hi>Bench,</hi> and forbad the Judges granting of <hi>Habeas Corpuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes?</hi> Can we then think theſe to be the <hi>practices</hi> of men, that ſtand for the <hi>liberty</hi> of the Subject?</p>
            <p>If they have forborne us in the <hi>libertie</hi> of our Perſons, they have paid us in the <hi>property</hi> of our Goods. Since they have applyed the <hi>ſword,</hi> we are ſo farre from recovery, that the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> they have made renders our <hi>cure</hi> worſe then ever our <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe</hi> was. Our <hi>property</hi> received a little <hi>ſcratch</hi> by the point of <hi>prerogative</hi> before, but now by the <hi>priviledge</hi> of Parliament
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:155794:25"/> the <hi>point</hi> of the ſword hath made the wound <hi>deſperate.</hi> When we read this queſtion propounded by one of their great <hi>Clerkes</hi> (in his anſwer to the frivolous paper, for ſo he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſtile the Petition for Peace:) <hi>Have they</hi> (the two Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) <hi>not us as at ſuch advantage, that they may undoe us every houre?</hi> Truly, till we had found they had made ſo ample <hi>proofe</hi> of their ability that way, we had thought it had been but a <hi>Paradox,</hi> or at moſt but an <hi>Article</hi> of their <hi>State-Creed;</hi> We never dream't it would have been made a <hi>piece</hi> of their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</hi> We muſt confeſſe you <hi>ſweetned</hi> the cup before you gave us our <hi>bane</hi> in it. Our reſtraint is mollified by the fine terme of <hi>ſecuring</hi> our perſons, (we pray this ſecuring may not be extended to cutting of our throats.) And for our <hi>eſtates,</hi> you are too mercifull to deſtroy them at <hi>one</hi> blow; you will have but a <hi>twentieth</hi> part at once, that they may <hi>conſume</hi> and <hi>bleed</hi> to death gently. What comes <hi>freely</hi> from us you accept of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and we had thought you had given us the <hi>publike faith</hi> for an <hi>Acquittance,</hi> (till we ſee you come now againe) that we might not have been <hi>couzened</hi> to pay the ſame ſcore <hi>twice</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. But we muſt tell you, when we are come to our <hi>ruine,</hi> it will be all one to us, whether we were led by the backe ſtaires with <hi>Ceremony,</hi> or thrown down <hi>headlong</hi> to it. And we take it more unkindly to be <hi>led</hi> downe by thoſe we put in truſt, then if we had been maliciouſly <hi>precipitated</hi> by others. And if you have forgotten the <hi>Antidote</hi> you gave us, we meane the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation,</hi> it workes too much upon us to be forgotten, and by vertue of that we ſhall joyne our ſelves to <hi>repell</hi> that violence, which hath been too long offered to the <hi>property</hi> of our <hi>eſtates,</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> of our perſons.</p>
            <p>Having taken this ſtrict view of ſo many particular <hi>preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and finding them but colourably alledged, what <hi>aires</hi> can we imagine, they ſhould heare ſo pleaſing in the ſound of the <hi>Drum</hi> and <hi>Trumpet,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bewitch them to continue this moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall and moſt bloudy Warre? And what advantage will accrue to the whole Kingdome (for we would not be engaged further in the quarrell for particular mens ends and benefit) to countervaile the charge of our expences? Is it the <hi>Militia</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:155794:25"/> that we fight for, and will nothing make you forbeare the <hi>uſe</hi> of the ſword, till you have gotten the full <hi>power</hi> of it? then we muſt profeſſe His Majeſty hath not given ſo much as a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable <hi>ground</hi> for this quarrell; unleſſe it be thought ground enough for his ſubjects to quarrell on, that His Majeſty does not as <hi>unreaſonably</hi> reſigne up all his juſt rights, as you demand them of Him. If His Majeſty delights in <hi>Peace,</hi> and to ſee His Subjects flouriſh under it, (as the long experience of His gracious diſpoſition ſheweth) what uſe have you for a <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia?</hi> I pray God reſtore us to that <hi>happineſſe</hi> which we enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when the <hi>ſword</hi> and <hi>ſheath</hi> too were both in the Kings own keeping. Is a Warre the way to <hi>conquer</hi> the Kings affections? and doe wee thinke to force Acts of grace from Him? Your <hi>ſword</hi> is like to be the way which God hath appointed for you to make Him glorious; but remember you may have need e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to find Him <hi>gracious,</hi> and therfore provoke His Majeſty no further unto a juſt <hi>ſeverity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is the quarrell continued for <hi>Delinquents?</hi> then you ſhould have done well to have ſet the King a <hi>precedent,</hi> in delivering Alderman <hi>Pennington</hi> and the reſt to a legall <hi>tryall.</hi> That would have been a faire invitation to His Majeſty to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned up thoſe that are about Him, to the proofe of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency. And whatever the Authour of <hi>Plaine Engliſh,</hi> and other ſeditious and ſchiſmaticall <hi>Clergy-men,</hi> (that cannot be preferred for their merit, and therefore ſeeke it by faction) what ever theſe men are affraid of, if you have retained the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of <hi>honeſt</hi> men, and worthy <hi>Patriots,</hi> you may dare to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the iſſue of a preſent <hi>Accommodation.</hi> And let me tell you, if <hi>thoſe</hi> about His Majeſty laying downe their <hi>relation</hi> to the Houſe of Parliament, (the priviledges whereof, if any were to this purpoſe, are as common and beneficiall to <hi>them,</hi> as to <hi>your ſelves)</hi> offer to ſubmit to a <hi>legall</hi> tryall (as Subjects ſhould doe) <hi>when the Government and knowne Lawes may have their free courſe;</hi> and you being under as <hi>high</hi> a charge, can plead nothing but <hi>priviledge</hi> of Parliament for your juſtification, and in the <hi>interim</hi> refuſe to ſubmit to the like <hi>legall</hi> tryall, you muſt needs be reputed <hi>Delinquents</hi> indeed, whileſt <hi>they</hi> are cleared
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:155794:26"/> by the <hi>verdict</hi> of every <hi>impartiall</hi> Judgement. And if you have gone ſo farre <hi>beyond</hi> and <hi>againſt</hi> the Law, that you are growne affraid to be try'd by it, what ſhall we conclude from hence but this, that you have undertaken this <hi>Warre</hi> in the proſecution of ſome <hi>new</hi> deſigne, and not (as hath been all this while pretended) for the ſecurity of our <hi>old</hi> Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Rights, and Liberties?</p>
            <p>That this deſigne was the <hi>ſubverſion</hi> of the <hi>ancient</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> is upon theſe <hi>grounds</hi> more then probable.</p>
            <p>That a <hi>change</hi> was aim'd at in the Church, no man can deny; and it is made evident, 1. By the <hi>ſuſpending</hi> of all Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Cenſures,</hi> (according to <hi>ancient</hi> Conſtitutions) inſomuch as <hi>Inceſt, Rapes,</hi> and all <hi>Vices</hi> have gone unpuniſhed: and this <hi>Jubilee</hi> of <hi>Indulgence</hi> hath drawne all <hi>offenders</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with them. 2. By ſetting the people a-worke (for ſome <hi>Cloſe-Committee</hi> was the firſt wheele that moved this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) to <hi>petition</hi> againſt the <hi>preſent Government</hi> and <hi>Service</hi> of the Church. 3. By the <hi>Bill</hi> long <hi>debated,</hi> and ſince <hi>conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on,</hi> for the <hi>aboliſhing</hi> of that <hi>Government.</hi> 4. By the chiefe perſons countenanced and imploy'd in the buſineſſe, who were <hi>Browniſts, Anabaptists,</hi> and all ſorts of <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Patrimony</hi> of the Church was to be <hi>alienated</hi> under a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> of eſtabliſhing a preaching Miniſter throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: but the truth is, if their <hi>zeale</hi> had been but in a <hi>ſeventh</hi> degree ſo <hi>hot</hi> for that good work, as it was for <hi>fighting</hi> for a <hi>bad</hi> one, they might have finiſht it for a <hi>twentieth</hi> part of that charge, which they have in a <hi>deſperate</hi> fury put the Kingdome to. Now we beleeve, if the <hi>Revenue</hi> of the Church were at their <hi>diſpoſall,</hi> they would change thoſe <hi>colours,</hi> (which they have worne ſo long for faſhion-ſake) and make the religious charity of their <hi>Anceſtors</hi> for the advancement of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, under a learned Miniſtry, ſerve onely to diſ-ingage their <hi>publike faith,</hi> which is not like to be a <hi>ſaving faith</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church had been <hi>ſubverted,</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:155794:26"/> the deſigne then was to be put in execution upon <hi>Monarchy:</hi> This is not a groundleſſe <hi>conjecture,</hi> if we conſider theſe <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Declaration</hi> upon the Earle of <hi>Straffords</hi> ſuffering, with this <hi>caution,</hi> that it might not be drawne into example for the future. Certainly this was with an eye to that <hi>ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of Government which themſelves (I mean the <hi>Projectors</hi> of this deſigne) intended; that being more guilty of the ſame <hi>crime,</hi> by vertue of ſuch a <hi>Declaration,</hi> they might be ſecured from the puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The pulling downe of ſo many <hi>Courts</hi> of Juſtice, (which were thought to be of very good uſe, in the time of our wiſe <hi>Anceſtors;</hi> and if there be no way of <hi>Reformation</hi> left, when <hi>exorbitances</hi> are crept into <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Callings,</hi> but their <hi>extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation,</hi> as their practice hath been of late, what will the <hi>doome</hi> be of the <hi>Supreme Court,</hi> and the ſeverall <hi>callings</hi> of the Kingdome?) with a notable blow at the <hi>Councell-Table.</hi> Theſe may relieve a <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>Subjects</hi> from ſome preſſures; but if ſomething be not ſetled in their <hi>roome,</hi> may encourage others in <hi>licenciouſneſſe,</hi> and prove the <hi>Prodromes</hi> (as we ſee by theſe beginnings) to the ruine of our <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>nineteen</hi> Propoſitions, whereby the King was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to lay downe His <hi>Crowne,</hi> to <hi>compound</hi> for His Peace with them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That expreſſion (ſo little underſtood, and ſo much talk't of in many of their <hi>papers)</hi> of a power of <hi>reſuming</hi> the truſt, which is falſly pretended to be <hi>derived unto His Majeſtie by the meere humane pactions and agreements of the politique body of the people.</hi> And,</p>
            <p n="5">5. According to this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> their pretending to, and uſurping of the power of the <hi>Militia,</hi> both by <hi>Sea</hi> and <hi>Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Their <hi>actuall exerciſing</hi> of this power in diſpoſing of <hi>offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> having made their <hi>Speaker</hi> Maſter of the Rolls.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, that expreſſion of the <hi>Gentlemen</hi> to Sir <hi>Edward Deering,</hi> (when he was <hi>privie</hi> to ſome of their <hi>Cabinet conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations) That if they could bring downe the Lords to the Houſe</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:155794:27"/> 
               <hi>of Commons, and make the King as one of the Lords, the worke were done.</hi> It ſeemes they intended to reſerve the honour of the <hi>Chaire</hi> for His <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> when they had taken downe His <hi>Throne;</hi> and it might have been His good fortune to have had a <hi>caſting</hi> voice, though he is now denied His <hi>negative</hi> one amongſt them. This <hi>plot</hi> was laid, and this <hi>deſigne</hi> in agitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (though it be a <hi>night-piece,</hi> which few have hitherto diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd fully) before the Warre commenced; and in order to this <hi>worke,</hi> without doubt the <hi>Militia</hi> was firſt exerciſed, and the <hi>Scots</hi> a ſecond time invited. (But we hope their <hi>Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners</hi> that taſted ſo much of the late <hi>feaſt,</hi> will not encourage their <hi>brethren</hi> to the <hi>fray.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When wee conſider theſe things, adding to them thoſe bloudy <hi>Treaſons</hi> uttered publikely (without checke) as well againſt the whole <hi>Line</hi> of the <hi>Bloud Royall,</hi> as againſt the <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred</hi> Perſon of our Soveraigne, and thoſe ſev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rall <hi>aſſaults</hi> made upon <hi>them;</hi> our <hi>haire</hi> begins to ſtand upright on our <hi>heads,</hi> and our <hi>conſciences</hi> often reflect upon our <hi>oathes</hi> of <hi>Allegeance</hi> and <hi>Supremacie,</hi> together with our late <hi>Protestation;</hi> whereby we ſtand obliged, to our utmoſt power, to maintaine His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Royall <hi>Perſon, Crowne</hi> and <hi>Dignity,</hi> againſt all treacherous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, that may ruine, diſhonour, or impaire them, and ſo by Gods help we will doe. And finding His <hi>Majeſties</hi> late Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions (as His Meſſages formerly) ſo juſt and reaſonable, as nothing can be more, and yet ſo little liſtened after for our peace: We adviſe all our <hi>Knights</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> to <hi>vote</hi> no more againſt our gracious <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> or the peace of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that they make no fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther uſe of our owne truſt to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us; for 'tis not our ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſe that they ſhould proceed to <hi>ſhed</hi> the bloud of the <hi>ungodly,</hi> (as they terme them) when they meane all ſuch as diſſent from their wilde opinions. And as we doe <hi>proteſt</hi> againſt ſuch <hi>Ordinances</hi> as are made againſt the <hi>King,</hi> or without His <hi>conſent,</hi> ſo ſhall we withdraw our <hi>truſt</hi> and power of <hi>repreſentation</hi> from ſuch as ſhall goe on to abuſe it. And finding no poſſibility of peace, till the <hi>packe</hi> (that contrived this <hi>new</hi> deſigne, and this Warre in order to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:155794:27"/> of it) be new <hi>ſhuffled,</hi> we ſhall joyntly labour to <hi>ſhuffle</hi> that <hi>packe,</hi> and diſſolve that <hi>knot</hi> wherein we ſee our miſeries are <hi>tryed;</hi> and (after due <hi>election</hi> of new <hi>Members</hi> into their places) reſolve to call them to a ſtrict <hi>account</hi> for betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our <hi>truſt,</hi> interrupting our <hi>peace,</hi> and violating all our <hi>ancient</hi> liberties, and ſhall not doubt of the aſſiſtance of all good men to effect it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 5. 6.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou, O God, ſhalt deſtroy them that ſpeake lies: The Lord will abhorre both the bloud-thirſty and deceitfull man.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
